------------------------------------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
The	O
following	O
report	O
summarizes	O
West	DIS
Nile	DIS
virus	DIS
-LRB-	O
WNV	DIS
-RRB-	O
surveillance	O
data	O
reported	O
to	O
CDC	ORGANIZATION
through	O
ArboNET	O
verified	O
by	O
states	O
jurisdictions	O
as	O
of	O
Tue	DATE
13	DATE
Nov	DATE
2001	DATE
.	O
During	O
the	DATE
week	DATE
of	DATE
Wed	DATE
7	NUMBER
to	O
Tue	DATE
13	DATE
Nov	DATE
2001	DATE
,	O
3	NUMBER
human	VIC
cases	VIC
of	O
WNV	DIS
encephalitis	DIS
or	DIS
meningitis	DIS
were	O
reported	O
from	O
New	LOCATION
York	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
2	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Louisiana	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
1	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
During	O
the	O
same	O
period	O
,	O
WNV	DIS
infections	DIS
were	O
reported	O
in	O
266	NUMBER
crows	VIC
,	O
15	NUMBER
other	VIC
birds	VIC
,	O
6	NUMBER
horses	VIC
.	O
A	O
total	O
of	O
17	NUMBER
WNV-positive	O
mosquito	O
pools	O
was	O
reported	O
from	O
2	NUMBER
jurisdictions	O
-LRB-	O
Pennsylvania	LOCATION
District	LOCATION
of	LOCATION
Columbia	LOCATION
-RRB-	O
.	O
During	O
2001	DATE
,	O
a	O
total	O
of	O
45	VIC
human	VIC
cases	VIC
of	O
WNV	DIS
encephalitis	DIS
or	DIS
meningitis	DIS
has	O
been	O
reported	O
from	O
New	LOCATION
York	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
12	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
,	O
Florida	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
10	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
,	O
Connecticut	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
6	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
,	O
Maryland	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
6	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
,	O
New	LOCATION
Jersey	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
6	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
,	O
Pennsylvania	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
3	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
,	O
Georgia	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
1	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
,	O
Louisiana	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
1	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
Among	O
these	O
45	VIC
cases	VIC
,	O
24	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
53	PERCENT
%	PERCENT
-RRB-	O
were	O
in	O
men	O
;	O
the	O
median	O
age	O
was	O
70	DURATION
years	DURATION
-LRB-	O
range	O
:	O
36	DURATION
to	DURATION
90	DURATION
years	DURATION
-RRB-	O
;	O
dates	O
of	O
illness	O
onset	O
ranged	O
from	O
13	DATE
Jul	DATE
to	O
7	DATE
Oct	DATE
2001	DATE
;	O
three	NUMBER
persons	O
died	O
.	O
During	O
2001	DATE
,	O
totals	O
of	O
4517	VIC
crows	VIC
and	VIC
1474	VIC
other	VIC
birds	VIC
with	O
WNV	DIS
infection	DIS
were	O
reported	O
from	O
26	NUMBER
states	O
the	O
District	LOCATION
of	LOCATION
Columbia	LOCATION
.	O
During	O
2001	DATE
,	O
176	NUMBER
WNV	DIS
infections	DIS
in	O
other	VIC
animals	VIC
-LRB-	O
all	VIC
horses	VIC
-RRB-	O
were	O
reported	O
from	O
14	NUMBER
states	O
-LRB-	O
Alabama	LOCATION
,	O
Connecticut	LOCATION
,	O
Florida	LOCATION
,	O
Georgia	LOCATION
,	O
Indiana	LOCATION
,	O
Kentucky	LOCATION
,	O
Louisiana	LOCATION
,	O
Massachusetts	LOCATION
,	O
Mississippi	LOCATION
,	O
New	LOCATION
York	LOCATION
,	O
North	LOCATION
Carolina	LOCATION
,	O
Pennsylvania	LOCATION
,	O
Tennessee	LOCATION
,	O
Virginia	LOCATION
-RRB-	O
.	O
During	O
2001	DATE
,	O
753	NUMBER
WNV-positive	O
mosquito	O
pools	O
were	O
reported	O
from	O
15	NUMBER
states	O
-LRB-	O
Connecticut	LOCATION
,	O
Florida	LOCATION
,	O
Georgia	LOCATION
,	O
Illinois	LOCATION
,	O
Kentucky	LOCATION
,	O
Maryland	LOCATION
,	O
Massachusetts	LOCATION
,	O
Michigan	LOCATION
,	O
New	LOCATION
Hampshire	LOCATION
,	O
New	LOCATION
Jersey	LOCATION
,	O
New	LOCATION
York	LOCATION
,	O
Ohio	LOCATION
,	O
Pennsylvania	LOCATION
,	O
Rhode	LOCATION
Island	LOCATION
,	O
Virginia	LOCATION
-RRB-	O
the	O
District	LOCATION
of	LOCATION
Columbia	LOCATION
.	O
Additional	O
information	O
about	O
WNV	DIS
activity	O
is	O
available	O
<	O
http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/dvbid/westnile/index.htm	NUMBER
>	O
<	O
http://cindi.usgs.gov/hazard/event/west_nile/west_nile.html	NUMBER
>	O
.	O
-LSB-	O
On	O
Wed	DATE
14	DATE
Nov	DATE
2001	DATE
,	O
2	NUMBER
additional	O
cases	VIC
of	O
human	VIC
West	DIS
Nile	DIS
virus	DIS
infection	DIS
were	O
reported	O
from	O
Massachusetts	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
the	O
first	ORDINAL
in	O
that	O
state	O
-RRB-	O
bringing	O
the	O
total	O
of	O
human	VIC
infections	DIS
to	O
at	VIC
least	VIC
47	VIC
for	O
the	O
2001	DATE
season	O
.	O
One	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
two	NUMBER
Massachusetts	LOCATION
patients	O
died	O
,	O
bringing	O
the	O
total	O
number	O
of	O
deaths	O
to	O
4	NUMBER
for	O
the	O
2001	DATE
season	O
according	O
to	O
the	O
above	O
figures	O
.	O
The	O
above	O
MMWR	ORGANIZATION
report	O
still	O
under-records	O
the	O
number	O
of	O
confirmed	O
equine	O
cases	VIC
in	O
2001	DATE
.	O
The	O
most	O
recent	O
USDA-APHIS	MISC
Report	MISC
covering	O
the	O
period	O
1	DATE
Jan	DATE
to	DATE
31	DATE
Oct	DATE
2001	DATE
-LRB-	O
see	O
:	O
West	DIS
Nile	DIS
virus	DIS
surveillance	O
-LRB-30-RRB-20011105	O
.2745	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
lists	O
344	NUMBER
confirmed	O
3	NUMBER
probable	O
cases	VIC
of	O
clinical	O
West	DIS
Nile	DIS
virus	DIS
-LRB-	O
WNV	DIS
-RRB-	O
infection	DIS
in	O
horses	VIC
from	O
18	NUMBER
States	O
.	O
-	O
Mod.CP	O
-RSB-	O
-LSB-	O
Note	O
that	O
posting	O
of	O
this	O
summary	O
was	O
delayed	O
.	O
An	O
additional	O
human	VIC
death	O
a	O
horse	O
death	O
have	O
been	O
reported	O
in	O
the	O
interim	O
-LRB-	O
see	O
ProMED-mail	O
references	O
cited	O
above	O
-RRB-	O
.	O
-	O
Mod.ES	O
-RSB-	O
...	O
cp/es	O
--------------------------------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
An	O
outbreak	O
of	O
what	O
is	O
suspected	O
to	O
be	O
winter	DATE
vomiting	O
disease	O
forced	O
closure	O
of	O
Sunnybrook	ORGANIZATION
Hospital	ORGANIZATION
's	O
emergency	O
department	O
on	O
Monday	DATE
morning	TIME
.	O
Over	O
weekend	DATE
,	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
patients	O
and	O
staff	O
were	O
stricken	O
by	O
bouts	O
of	O
vomiting	O
and	O
diarrhea	O
.	O
By	O
Monday	DATE
afternoon	TIME
25	DATE
Nov	DATE
2002	DATE
,	O
28	NUMBER
staff	O
members	O
and	O
13	NUMBER
patients	O
showed	O
symptoms	O
of	O
the	DIS
virus	DIS
infection	O
,	O
which	O
is	O
highly	O
contagious	O
and	O
spread	O
through	O
person-to-person	O
contact	O
.	O
``	O
We	O
have	O
n't	O
determined	O
what	O
infection	O
is	O
yet	O
.	O
We	O
suspect	O
it	O
to	O
be	O
a	O
case	O
of	O
something	O
called	O
winter	DATE
vomiting	O
disease	O
,	O
''	O
hospital	O
spokesman	O
Craig	PERSON
DuHamel	PERSON
said	O
.	O
``	O
Obviously	O
we	O
have	O
to	O
be	O
very	O
vigilant	O
to	O
ensure	O
this	O
is	O
contained	O
in	O
our	O
emergency	O
department	O
.	O
''	O
The	O
emergency	O
department	O
was	O
expected	O
to	O
be	O
closed	O
until	O
afternoon	TIME
of	TIME
Wed	DATE
27	DATE
Nov	DATE
2002	DATE
at	O
least	O
,	O
DuHamel	PERSON
said	O
,	O
adding	O
that	O
cleaning	O
crews	O
were	O
on	O
scene	O
with	O
anti-viral	O
agents	O
-LSB-	O
disinfectants	O
?	O
-RSB-	O
.	O
Patients	O
walking	O
into	O
emergency	O
were	O
told	O
about	O
situation	O
upon	O
arrival	O
and	O
,	O
if	O
their	O
condition	O
was	O
stable	O
,	O
asked	O
to	O
go	O
to	O
another	O
hospital	O
.	O
Those	O
who	O
were	O
unable	O
to	O
go	O
to	O
another	O
facility	O
would	O
be	O
treated	O
,	O
hospital	O
said	O
in	O
a	O
news	O
release	O
.	O
Winter	DATE
vomiting	O
disease	O
is	O
an	O
infection	O
caused	O
by	O
a	O
virus	DIS
commonly	O
transmitted	O
from	O
person	O
to	O
person	O
in	O
cold	O
weather	O
,	O
when	O
people	O
are	O
indoors	O
more	O
often	O
and	O
in	O
closer	O
contact	O
.	O
Symptoms	O
include	O
severe	O
nausea	O
and	O
vomiting	O
that	O
can	O
last	O
between	O
24	NUMBER
and	O
48	DURATION
hours	DURATION
.	O
DuHamel	PERSON
said	O
the	DIS
virus	DIS
is	O
not	O
life-threatening	O
and	O
is	O
similar	O
to	O
the	DIS
Norwalk	DIS
virus	DIS
,	O
which	O
has	O
made	O
headlines	O
recently	DATE
for	O
sickening	O
hundreds	VIC
of	O
passengers	VIC
on	O
Florida-based	MISC
cruise	O
ship	O
Amsterdam	LOCATION
.	O
-LSB-	O
As	O
has	O
been	O
repeatedly	O
stated	O
in	O
ProMED-mail	LOCATION
,	O
``	O
winter	DATE
vomiting	O
disease	O
''	O
is	O
a	O
misnomer	O
.	O
Outbreaks	O
in	O
UK	LOCATION
and	O
Ireland	LOCATION
have	O
occurred	O
throughout	O
year	DATE
in	O
hospitals	O
,	O
health	O
care	O
facilities	O
,	O
and	O
schools	O
.	O
In	O
North	LOCATION
America	LOCATION
outbreaks	O
on	O
cruise	O
ships	O
have	O
occurred	O
during	O
voyages	O
to	O
Alaska	LOCATION
in	O
summer	DATE
and	O
to	O
Caribbean	LOCATION
destinations	O
in	O
winter	DATE
.	O
Density	O
and	O
hygiene	O
considerations	O
are	O
probably	O
relevant	O
determining	O
factors	O
.	O
Winter	DATE
vomiting	O
disease	O
is	O
caused	O
by	O
infection	O
with	O
a	O
Norwalk-like	MISC
virus	DIS
,	O
although	O
this	O
is	O
seldom	O
confirmed	O
microbiologically	O
.	O
Norwalk-like	O
viruses	O
are	O
a	O
heterogenous	O
group	O
of	O
caliciviruses	O
that	O
is	O
now	DATE
designated	O
as	O
genus	O
_	NUMBER
Norovirus	MISC
_	O
.	O
-	O
Mod.CP	O
-RSB-	O
--	O
ProMED-mail	O
<promed@promedmail.org>	O
-------------------------------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
The	O
Minas	ORGANIZATION
Gerais	ORGANIZATION
State	ORGANIZATION
Secretary	O
of	O
Health	O
confirms	O
16	VIC
cases	VIC
-LRB-	O
8	NUMBER
fatal	O
-RRB-	O
due	O
to	O
hantavirus	DIS
infection	DIS
in	O
the	O
state	O
so	O
far	O
in	O
2003	DATE
,	O
with	O
another	VIC
6	VIC
suspect	VIC
cases	VIC
under	O
investigation	O
.	O
The	O
results	O
of	O
confirmatory	O
laboratory	O
tests	O
will	O
be	O
available	O
in	O
10	DURATION
days	DURATION
.	O
In	O
all	O
of	O
2002	DATE
there	O
were	O
14	VIC
cases	VIC
with	O
7	NUMBER
deaths	O
.	O
The	O
outbreak	O
is	O
being	O
studied	O
by	O
specialists	O
from	O
the	O
Instituto	PERSON
Adolfo	PERSON
Lutz	PERSON
of	O
Sao	LOCATION
Paulo	LOCATION
.	O
two	NUMBER
of	O
them	O
from	O
the	O
same	O
city	O
office	O
building	O
,	O
health	O
authorities	O
said	O
today	DATE
.	O
Victoria	PERSON
's	O
Chief	O
Health	O
Officer	O
Dr	O
Graham	PERSON
Rouch	PERSON
said	O
the	O
other	O
three	NUMBER
patients	O
may	O
also	O
be	O
linked	O
to	O
the	O
same	O
area	O
of	O
Melbourne	LOCATION
's	O
Exhibition	O
Street	O
.	O
With	O
the	O
latest	O
outbreak	O
,	O
Dr	O
Rouch	PERSON
urged	O
city	O
dwellers	O
,	O
office	O
workers	O
and	O
visitors	O
to	O
be	O
alert	O
to	O
the	O
signs	O
of	O
the	O
disease	DIS
.	O
He	O
said	O
that	O
two	NUMBER
with	O
the	O
disease	DIS
-	O
among	O
three	NUMBER
being	O
treated	O
in	O
hospital	O
-	O
worked	O
at	O
222	NUMBER
Exhibition	O
Street	O
.	O
One	NUMBER
was	O
employed	O
by	O
the	O
Transport	ORGANIZATION
Accident	ORGANIZATION
Commission	ORGANIZATION
and	O
the	O
other	O
by	O
the	O
Victorian	ORGANIZATION
Workcover	ORGANIZATION
Authority	ORGANIZATION
.	O
Staff	O
and	O
other	O
tenants	O
in	O
the	O
building	O
have	O
been	O
given	O
information	O
about	O
the	O
disease	DIS
.	O
Dr	O
Rouch	PERSON
said	O
the	O
early	O
stages	O
of	O
legionnaire	O
's	O
disease	DIS
was	O
characterised	O
by	O
flu-like	O
symptoms	O
,	O
including	O
headache	O
,	O
fever	O
,	O
muscle	O
aches	O
and	O
respiratory	O
problems	O
.	O
The	O
most	O
usual	O
method	O
of	O
transmission	O
of	O
the	O
infection	O
was	O
via	O
spray	O
drift	O
from	O
air	O
conditioning	O
towers	O
.	O
He	O
said	O
Human	ORGANIZATION
Services	ORGANIZATION
Department	ORGANIZATION
officials	O
took	O
samples	O
from	O
cooling	O
towers	O
at	O
222	NUMBER
Exhibition	O
Street	O
and	O
were	O
awaiting	O
confirmation	O
of	O
the	O
results	O
.	O
He	O
said	O
the	O
towers	O
had	O
been	O
disinfected	O
as	O
a	O
precaution	O
.	O
Dr	O
Rouch	PERSON
said	O
the	O
recent	O
hot	O
weather	O
in	O
Melbourne	LOCATION
had	O
put	O
a	O
considerable	O
extra	O
load	O
on	O
cooling	O
systems	O
,	O
`	O
which	O
may	O
have	O
provided	O
a	O
better	O
environment	O
for	O
_	NUMBER
Legionella	PERSON
_	NUMBER
to	O
multiply	O
'	O
.	O
--	O
ProMED-mail	O
e-mail	O
:	O
promed@promedmail.org......................................es	O
--	O
Department	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Crop	ORGANIZATION
Sciences	ORGANIZATION
,	O
University	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Illinois	ORGANIZATION
;	O
and	O
G.	PERSON
L.	PERSON
Hartman	PERSON
,	O
USDA	ORGANIZATION
,	O
ARS	ORGANIZATION
,	O
and	O
Department	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Crop	ORGANIZATION
Sciences	ORGANIZATION
,	O
University	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Illinois	ORGANIZATION
,	O
1101	DATE
W.	PERSON
Peabody	PERSON
Dr.	PERSON
,	O
Urbana	LOCATION
61801	NUMBER
.	O
Plant	O
Dis	O
.	O
84:100	O
,	O
2000	DATE
;	O
published	O
on-line	O
as	O
D-1999-1117-01N	DATE
1999	DATE
.	O
Accepted	O
for	O
publication	O
12	DATE
November	DATE
1999	DATE
.	O
_	O
Stachybotrys	DIS
chartarum	DIS
_	O
-LRB-	O
Ehrenb	DIS
.	O
ex	DIS
Link	DIS
-RRB-	O
S.J.	PERSON
Hughes	PERSON
was	O
isolated	O
from	O
surface-disinfested	VIC
soybean	VIC
-LRB-	O
Glycine	VIC
max	VIC
-LRB-	O
L.	O
-RRB-	O
Merr	VIC
.	O
-RRB-	O
root	O
lesions	O
.	O
The	O
fungus	O
was	O
cultured	O
on	O
potato	O
dextrose	O
agar	O
,	O
and	O
its	O
morphology	O
was	O
examined	O
by	O
light	O
and	O
environmental	O
scanning	O
electron	O
microscopy	O
.	O
Conidiophores	O
were	O
determinate	O
,	O
macronematous	O
,	O
solitary	O
or	O
in	O
groups	O
,	O
and	O
simple	O
or	O
irregularly	O
branched	O
.	O
Phialides	PERSON
occurred	O
in	O
whorls	O
and	O
were	O
obovate	O
or	O
ellipsoidal	O
.	O
Conidia	O
were	O
unicellular	O
,	O
round	O
to	O
ellipsoidal	O
,	O
5	NUMBER
to	O
13	NUMBER
4	NUMBER
to	O
7	NUMBER
m	O
,	O
initially	O
hyaline	O
,	O
smooth-walled	O
,	O
and	O
dark	O
brown	O
to	O
black	O
and	O
rough-walled	O
when	O
mature	O
.	O
A	O
pure	O
culture	O
obtained	O
from	O
infected	VIC
soy-bean	VIC
roots	VIC
was	O
used	O
to	O
test	O
pathogenicity	O
under	O
greenhouse	O
and	O
growth-chamber	O
conditions	O
.	O
_	O
S.	O
chartarum	DIS
_	O
was	O
grown	O
on	O
sterilized	O
sorghum	O
grain	O
for	O
2	DURATION
weeks	DURATION
and	O
placed	O
in	O
soil	O
2	NUMBER
to	O
3	NUMBER
cm	O
below	O
sown	O
soybean	VIC
seeds	O
.	O
Noninfested	O
sorghum	O
grain	O
was	O
used	O
as	O
a	O
control	O
.	O
All	O
soybean	VIC
plants	O
inoculated	O
with	O
_	NUMBER
S.	O
chartarum	DIS
_	O
had	O
root	O
lesions	O
ranging	O
from	O
7	NUMBER
to	NUMBER
25	NUMBER
mm	O
21	DURATION
days	DURATION
after	O
sowing	O
,	O
while	O
control	O
plants	O
did	O
not	O
have	O
any	O
measurable	O
root	O
rot	O
.	O
The	O
DNA	O
sequence	O
of	O
the	O
internal	O
transcribed	O
spacer	O
-LRB-	O
ITS	O
-RRB-	O
region	O
was	O
100	PERCENT
%	PERCENT
identical	O
to	O
_	O
S.	O
chartarum	DIS
_	O
strain	DIS
ATCC	DIS
9182	DIS
-LRB-	O
1	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
but	O
differed	O
from	O
all	O
published	O
sequences	O
of	O
other	O
_	O
Stachybotrys	DIS
_	O
and	O
_	O
Memnoniella	PERSON
_	NUMBER
spp	O
.	O
in	O
Gen-Bank	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
1	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
Polymerase	O
chain	O
reaction	O
with	O
_	NUMBER
S.	O
chartarum	DIS
_	O
-	O
specific	O
primer	O
StacR3	O
and	O
IT51	O
-LRB-	O
1	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
amplified	O
a	O
198-bp	O
DNA	MISC
fragment	O
from	O
the	O
total	O
genomic	O
DNA	O
.	O
The	O
molecular	O
evidence	O
further	O
supports	O
the	O
identification	O
of	O
_	O
S.	O
chartarum	DIS
_	O
isolated	O
from	O
soybean	VIC
.	O
This	O
is	O
the	O
first	ORDINAL
report	O
of	O
_	O
S.	O
chartarum	DIS
_	O
causing	O
soybean	VIC
root	O
rot	O
.	O
Reference	O
:	O
R.	PERSON
A.	PERSON
Haugland	PERSON
and	O
J.	PERSON
L.	PERSON
Heckman	PERSON
.	O
Mol	O
.	O
Cell	O
.	O
Probes	O
12:387	NUMBER
,	O
1998	DATE
.	O
-LSB-	O
_	NUMBER
Stachybotrys	DIS
chartarum	DIS
_	O
also	O
causes	O
disease	O
in	O
humans	O
and	O
animals	O
through	O
the	O
action	O
of	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
mycotoxins	O
,	O
including	O
trichothecenes	O
.	O
The	O
fungus	O
also	O
produces	O
9-phenylspirodrimanes	O
and	O
cyclosporin	O
which	O
are	O
potent	O
immunosuppressive	O
agents	O
.	O
Two	NUMBER
good	O
references	O
can	O
be	O
found	O
at	O
the	O
following	O
URLs	O
:	O
<	O
http://psychiatry.medscape.com/Medscape/GeneralMedicine/journal/public/mgm.journal.html	O
>	O
<	O
http://www.scisoc.org/feature/stachybotrys/Top.html	O
>	O
-	O
Mod	O
.	O
DH	O
-RSB-	O
...	O
dh/ds	O
------------------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
Between	O
29	DATE
Apr	DATE
and	O
3	DATE
May	DATE
2001	DATE
,	O
158	NUMBER
cases	VIC
of	O
acute	O
dysentery	DIS
have	O
been	O
registered	O
among	O
patients	O
in	O
the	O
Kaluga	LOCATION
province	O
psychiatric	O
hospital	O
-LRB-	O
for	O
692	NUMBER
people	O
-RRB-	O
.	O
23	NUMBER
people	O
have	O
been	O
hospitalized	O
.	O
The	O
disease	O
occurred	O
in	O
mild	O
and	O
moderate	O
to	O
serious	O
forms	O
.	O
The	O
diagnosis	O
has	O
been	O
confirmed	O
bacteriologically	O
by	O
isolation	O
of	O
strain	DIS
of	O
_	NUMBER
Shigella	O
flexneri	O
_	NUMBER
2a	O
from	O
66	NUMBER
people	O
.	O
The	O
outbreak	O
is	O
food-borne	O
and	O
associated	O
with	O
use	O
of	O
a	DIS
curd	O
pudding	O
that	O
has	O
been	O
prepared	O
with	O
-LSB-	O
violation	O
-RSB-	O
of	O
-LSB-	O
proper	O
food	O
preparation	O
practices	O
-RSB-	O
in	O
the	O
hospital	O
kitchen	O
on	O
27	DATE
Apr	DATE
2001	DATE
.	O
The	O
cook	O
was	O
found	O
during	O
bacteriological	O
investigation	O
to	O
be	O
an	O
active	O
-LSB-	O
carrier	O
-RSB-	O
and	O
was	O
supposed	O
to	O
be	O
the	O
infectious	O
source	O
.	O
Specialists	O
from	O
the	O
center	O
for	O
sanitary	O
and	O
epidemiological	O
surveillance	O
in	O
Kaluga	LOCATION
province	O
are	O
carrying	O
out	O
an	O
epidemic	O
investigation	O
.	O
*****	O
-LSB-	O
2	NUMBER
-RSB-	O
Source	O
:	O
ITAR-TASS	ORGANIZATION
News	ORGANIZATION
Agency	ORGANIZATION
,	O
5	DATE
May	DATE
2001	DATE
-LSB-	O
edited	O
-RSB-	O
KALUGA	LOCATION
:	O
The	O
dysentery	DIS
outbreak	O
among	O
patients	O
of	O
the	O
province	O
psychiatric	O
hospital	O
has	O
waned	O
.	O
Today	DATE
49	NUMBER
patients	O
are	O
in	O
hospital	O
.	O
On	O
Friday	DATE
-LSB-	O
4	DATE
May	DATE
2001	DATE
-RSB-	O
there	O
were	O
almost	O
twice	O
as	O
many	O
patients	O
.	O
According	O
to	O
Anatoly	PERSON
Fadeev	PERSON
,	O
chief	O
state	O
sanitary	O
physician	O
in	O
Kaluga	LOCATION
province	LOCATION
,	O
21	NUMBER
patients	O
are	O
situated	O
in	O
the	O
infectious	O
department	O
,	O
and	O
28	NUMBER
in	O
the	O
isolation	O
ward	O
.	O
9	NUMBER
patients	O
have	O
a	DIS
moderate	O
or	O
serious	O
-LSB-	O
form	O
-RSB-	O
of	O
the	O
disease	O
.	O
For	O
the	DURATION
7	DURATION
days	DURATION
from	O
the	O
beginning	O
of	O
the	O
outbreak	O
more	O
than	O
900	NUMBER
people	O
,	O
who	O
could	O
be	O
infected	O
,	O
have	O
been	O
observed	O
.	O
The	O
cooks	O
were	O
a	DIS
source	O
of	O
the	O
infection	O
,	O
said	O
Anatoly	PERSON
Fadeev	PERSON
.	O
At	O
the	O
present	DATE
time	O
prophylactic	O
and	O
treatment	O
measures	O
for	O
localization	O
and	O
liquidation	O
of	O
the	O
outbreak	O
are	O
continuing	O
.	O
*****	O
-LSB-	O
3	NUMBER
-RSB-	O
Source	O
:	O
Official	O
information	O
from	O
the	O
Website	O
of	O
the	O
Health	ORGANIZATION
Ministry	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
the	ORGANIZATION
Russian	ORGANIZATION
Federation	ORGANIZATION
-LRB-	O
Outbreaks	O
News	O
Website	O
,	O
in	O
Russian	MISC
-RRB-	O
,	O
4	DATE
May	DATE
2001	DATE
-LSB-	O
edited	O
-RSB-	O
<	O
http://www.depart.drureg.ru/hotline/	NUMBER
>	O
Between	O
24	DATE
Apr	DATE
and	O
1	DATE
May	DATE
2001	DATE
93	VIC
cases	VIC
of	O
dysentery	DIS
-LRB-	O
including	O
54	NUMBER
children	O
under	O
14	DURATION
years	DURATION
of	O
age	O
-RRB-	O
have	O
been	O
registered	O
among	O
residents	O
of	O
Verkhnee	LOCATION
Lyukino	LOCATION
village	O
-LRB-	O
345	NUMBER
people	O
-RRB-	O
,	O
Blezinsky	PERSON
region	O
,	O
Udmurtskaya	LOCATION
Republic	LOCATION
.	O
The	O
disease	O
has	O
mild	O
and	O
moderate	O
to	O
serious	O
course	O
.	O
A	O
bacteriological	O
diagnosis	O
has	O
been	O
obtained	O
for	O
71	NUMBER
people	O
:	O
a	DIS
_	O
Shigella	O
sonnei	DIS
_	NUMBER
strain	DIS
has	O
been	O
isolated	O
from	O
them	O
.	O
New	O
cases	VIC
have	O
not	O
been	O
registered	O
since	O
2	DATE
May	DATE
2001	DATE
.	O
The	O
infectious	O
source	O
is	O
drinking	O
water	O
infected	O
from	O
the	O
sewerage	O
after	O
a	DIS
disaster	O
in	O
water	O
supply	O
on	O
23	DATE
Apr	DATE
2001	DATE
.	O
Specialists	O
from	O
the	O
center	O
of	O
the	O
state	O
sanitary	O
and	O
epidemiological	O
surveillance	O
and	O
health	O
ministry	O
of	O
the	O
republic	O
are	O
carrying	O
out	O
the	O
epidemiological	O
investigation	O
.	O
-LSB-	O
These	O
2	NUMBER
outbreaks	O
illustrate	O
one	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
public	O
health	O
impacts	O
of	O
continued	O
problems	O
with	O
infrastructure	O
maintenance	O
in	O
Russia	LOCATION
and	O
other	O
regions	O
of	O
the	O
former	O
Soviet	LOCATION
Union	LOCATION
.	O
-	O
Mod.ES	O
-RSB-	O
...	O
mpp/av/es	O
/	O
ds	O
--------------------------------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
During	O
Cuban	MISC
neuropathy	DIS
outbreak	O
in	O
1992-1993	DATE
,	O
we	O
worked	O
-LSB-	O
in	O
collaboration	O
with	O
team	O
investigating	O
-RSB-	O
theories	O
concerning	O
a	O
possible	O
toxic-nutritional	O
physiopathological	O
origin	O
and	O
-LSB-	O
involvement	O
of	O
oxidative	O
stress	O
-RSB-	O
.	O
Later	O
our	O
team	O
,	O
with	O
French	MISC
research	O
partners	O
,	O
developed	O
different	O
prospective	O
studies	O
-LRB-	O
SECUBA	O
program	O
1995	DATE
1997	DATE
-RRB-	O
in	O
healthy	O
volunteers	O
and	O
patients	O
with	O
neuropathy	DIS
,	O
-LSB-	O
establishing	O
-RSB-	O
central	O
role	O
of	O
antioxidants	O
,	O
energy	O
,	O
and	O
oxidative	O
stress	O
in	O
Cuban	MISC
neuropathy	DIS
outbreak	O
.	O
We	O
were	O
aware	O
of	O
the	DIS
Tanzanian	DIS
epidemic	DIS
of	O
bilateral	DIS
optic	DIS
neuropathy	DIS
-LRB-	O
Dolin	ORGANIZATION
PJ	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Mohamed	ORGANIZATION
AA	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Plant	O
GT	O
.	O
Epidemic	O
of	O
bilateral	DIS
optic	DIS
neuropathy	DIS
in	O
Dar	LOCATION
es	LOCATION
Salaam	LOCATION
,	O
Tanzania	LOCATION
.	O
N	O
Engl	O
J	O
Med	O
1998	DATE
;	O
338:1547	NUMBER
-8	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
-LSB-	O
Although	O
-RSB-	O
most	O
recent	O
information	O
is	O
limited	O
,	O
-LSB-	O
a	O
significant	O
difference	O
between	O
Cuban	MISC
and	O
Tanzanian	DIS
outbreaks	O
-RSB-	O
is	O
that	O
no	O
deaths	O
occurred	O
in	O
Cuban	MISC
neuropathy	DIS
outbreak	O
.	O
Nonetheless	O
we	O
are	O
always	O
interested	O
in	O
assisting	O
any	O
country	O
,	O
including	O
Tanzania	LOCATION
,	O
-LSB-	O
that	O
suspects	O
occurrence	O
-RSB-	O
of	O
an	O
epidemic	DIS
neuropathy	DIS
outbreak	O
of	O
type	O
experienced	O
in	O
Cuba	LOCATION
.	O
In	O
Cuba	LOCATION
disease	O
is	O
no	O
longer	O
a	O
problem	O
,	O
and	O
solution	O
was	O
related	O
to	O
improvements	O
in	O
diet	O
,	O
particularly	O
antioxidants	O
-LSB-	O
supplied	O
-RSB-	O
by	O
vegetables	O
and	O
fruits	O
,	O
even	O
if	O
-LSB-	O
overall	O
-RSB-	O
levels	O
of	O
calories	O
and	O
some	O
-LSB-	O
other	O
-RSB-	O
nutrients	O
-LRB-	O
e.g.	O
,	O
B	O
vitamins	O
-RRB-	O
were	O
not	O
entirely	O
adequate	O
.	O
Lifestyle	O
was	O
also	O
important	O
.	O
-LSB-	O
Dr	O
Verdura	PERSON
's	O
comments	O
may	O
refer	O
to	O
2	NUMBER
separate	O
events	O
,	O
namely	O
outbreak	O
of	O
epidemic	DIS
neuropathy	DIS
in	O
coastal	O
region	O
of	O
Tanzania	LOCATION
and	O
an	O
outbreak	O
of	O
an	O
unidentified	O
illness	O
affecting	O
mainly	O
young	O
men	O
on	O
Ukerewe	LOCATION
Island	LOCATION
,	O
Tanzania	LOCATION
.	O
I	O
have	O
edited	O
Dr	O
Verdura	PERSON
's	O
remarks	O
-LRB-	O
I	O
hope	O
correctly	O
-RRB-	O
to	O
relate	O
mainly	O
to	O
first	ORDINAL
of	O
these	O
2	NUMBER
events	O
.	O
-	O
Mod.CP	O
-RSB-	O
-LSB-	O
Dr	O
Verdura	PERSON
rightly	O
points	O
out	O
that	O
the	DIS
epidemic	DIS
neuropathy	DIS
seen	O
in	O
Cuba	LOCATION
was	O
not	O
associated	O
with	O
mortality	O
.	O
A	O
review	O
of	O
limited	O
postings	O
on	O
the	DIS
epidemic	DIS
neuropathy	DIS
in	O
Tanzania	LOCATION
Coastal	O
area	O
does	O
not	O
mention	O
mortality	O
either	O
.	O
This	O
moderator	O
significantly	O
erred	O
by	O
provocative	O
comments	O
made	O
in	O
posting	O
Unexplained	O
deaths	O
-	O
Tanzania	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
Ukerewe	LOCATION
Island	LOCATION
-RRB-	O
-LRB-	O
02	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
:	O
RFI20030529	O
.1314	NUMBER
,	O
suggesting	O
there	O
might	O
be	O
a	O
link	O
between	O
the	DIS
epidemic	DIS
neuropathy	DIS
reported	O
in	O
coast	O
of	O
Tanzania	LOCATION
and	O
undiagnosed	O
deaths	O
in	O
young	O
males	O
on	O
Ukerewe	LOCATION
Island	LOCATION
.	O
A	O
late	TIME
night	TIME
fruit	O
salad	O
mixing	O
of	O
apples	O
and	O
oranges	O
.	O
-	O
Mod.MPP	O
-RSB-	O
-------------------------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
A	VIC
man	VIC
has	O
been	O
admitted	O
to	O
hospital	O
in	DIS
Scotland	LOCATION
with	O
an	DIS
acute	O
neurological	O
illness	DIS
that	O
is	O
being	O
investigated	O
as	O
a	VIC
suspected	O
case	DIS
of	O
rabies	DIS
-LRB-	O
1,2	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
The	DIS
possible	O
diagnosis	O
of	O
a	VIC
rabies-like	DIS
illness	DIS
is	O
being	O
considered	O
because	O
of	O
some	O
aspects	O
of	O
clinical	O
presentation	O
and	O
because	O
the	VIC
man	VIC
is	O
a	VIC
bat	VIC
handler	O
who	O
has	O
been	O
bitten	O
by	O
a	VIC
bat	VIC
in	DIS
Scotland	LOCATION
on	O
at	O
least	O
one	NUMBER
occasion	O
within	O
possible	O
incubation	O
period	O
for	O
rabies	DIS
.	O
There	O
is	O
no	O
documented	O
evidence	O
that	O
the	VIC
patient	VIC
has	O
ever	O
received	O
rabies	DIS
immunisation	O
or	O
has	O
travelled	O
abroad	O
since	O
1996	DATE
.	O
Although	O
clinical	O
features	O
of	O
the	VIC
man	VIC
's	O
illness	DIS
are	O
compatible	O
with	O
some	O
aspects	O
of	O
rabies	DIS
,	O
none	O
of	O
laboratory	O
investigations	O
yet	O
indicates	O
that	O
a	VIC
rabies-like	DIS
virus	DIS
is	O
responsible	O
.	O
Testing	O
for	O
rabies	DIS
and	O
rabies-like	DIS
virus	DIS
is	O
not	O
,	O
however	O
,	O
straightforward	O
and	O
more	O
tests	O
are	O
being	O
undertaken	O
.	O
The	DIS
case	DIS
has	O
raised	O
awareness	O
of	O
possibility	O
of	O
rabies-like	DIS
virus	DIS
infection	DIS
of	O
bats	VIC
in	DIS
United	LOCATION
Kingdom	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
UK	VIC
-RRB-	O
-LRB-	O
3	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
European	DIS
bat	VIC
lyssavirus	DIS
:	O
The	DIS
rabies-like	DIS
viruses	DIS
carried	O
by	O
insectivorous	O
bats	VIC
in	DIS
Europe	LOCATION
are	O
referred	O
to	O
as	O
European	DIS
bat	VIC
lyssaviruses	DIS
-LRB-	O
EBLs	DIS
-RRB-	O
.	O
These	O
are	O
from	O
same	O
family	O
of	O
viruses	DIS
that	O
cause	O
rabies	DIS
in	DIS
terrestrial	O
mammals	O
and	O
in	DIS
bats	VIC
in	DIS
Americas	LOCATION
,	O
but	O
differ	O
in	DIS
genotype	O
and	O
serotype	O
.	O
They	O
are	O
EBL	DIS
1	DIS
and	O
2	DIS
,	O
and	O
are	O
of	O
rabies	DIS
virus	DIS
genotype	O
5	NUMBER
and	O
6	NUMBER
,	O
respectively	O
.	O
Classical	O
rabies	DIS
is	O
due	O
to	O
rabies	DIS
virus	DIS
genotype	O
1	DIS
.	O
Between	O
1977	DATE
and	O
2000	DATE
,	O
630	NUMBER
cases	O
of	O
EBL	DIS
infection	DIS
in	DIS
bats	VIC
were	O
reported	O
in	DIS
Europe	LOCATION
,	O
mostly	O
in	DIS
Denmark	LOCATION
,	O
Netherlands	LOCATION
,	O
and	O
Germany	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
4	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
Only	DIS
2	DIS
EBL	DIS
infections	DIS
have	O
been	O
confirmed	O
in	DIS
UK	VIC
bats	VIC
:	O
one	NUMBER
on	O
south	O
coast	O
of	O
England	LOCATION
in	DIS
1996	DATE
-LRB-	O
5	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
and	O
another	O
in	DIS
northwest	O
England	LOCATION
in	DIS
2002	DATE
-LRB-	O
6,7	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
Both	O
of	O
these	O
bat	VIC
rabies	DIS
infections	DIS
were	O
in	DIS
same	O
species	VIC
--	O
Daubenton	PERSON
's	O
bat	VIC
.	O
In	O
case	DIS
in	DIS
1996	DATE
it	O
was	O
thought	O
that	O
the	VIC
bat	VIC
might	O
have	O
migrated	O
from	O
continental	O
Europe	LOCATION
.	O
The	DIS
location	O
of	O
2002	DATE
Lancashire	LOCATION
case	DIS
is	O
,	O
however	O
,	O
more	O
consistent	O
with	O
EBLs	DIS
being	O
present	DATE
in	DIS
a	VIC
bat	VIC
species	VIC
in	DIS
the	VIC
UK	VIC
.	O
The	DIS
Veterinary	ORGANIZATION
Laboratories	ORGANIZATION
Agency	ORGANIZATION
in	DIS
the	VIC
UK	VIC
tests	O
about	O
200	NUMBER
bats	VIC
every	SET
year	SET
for	O
EBL	DIS
,	O
but	O
has	O
not	O
so	O
far	O
detected	O
virus	DIS
other	O
than	O
2	DIS
cases	O
in	DIS
1996	DATE
and	O
2002	DATE
-LRB-	O
8	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
EBLs	DIS
do	O
not	O
readily	O
cross	O
the	VIC
species	VIC
barrier	O
,	O
and	O
even	O
in	DIS
parts	O
of	O
Europe	LOCATION
where	O
bats	VIC
are	O
known	O
to	O
carry	O
EBLs	DIS
,	O
it	O
is	O
very	O
rare	O
for	O
other	O
animals	O
to	O
be	O
infected	O
-LRB-	O
9	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
The	DIS
risk	O
of	O
EBL	DIS
infection	DIS
being	O
passed	O
to	O
domestic	O
pets	O
such	O
as	O
dogs	O
and	O
cats	O
,	O
and	O
to	O
wild	O
terrestrial	O
mammals	O
,	O
is	O
very	O
low	O
,	O
and	O
rabies-free	O
status	O
of	O
the	VIC
UK	VIC
has	O
been	O
unaffected	O
by	O
previous	O
isolation	O
of	O
EBL	DIS
in	DIS
2	DIS
bats	VIC
in	DIS
the	VIC
UK	VIC
.	O
As	O
EBL	DIS
does	O
not	O
transmit	O
readily	O
to	O
other	O
species	VIC
,	O
infection	DIS
in	DIS
humans	DIS
is	O
extremely	O
rare	O
.	O
Only	DIS
3	NUMBER
human	O
cases	O
have	O
been	O
reported	O
in	DIS
Europe	LOCATION
since	O
1977	DATE
,	O
one	NUMBER
in	DIS
Finland	LOCATION
and	O
2	DIS
in	DIS
former	O
Soviet	LOCATION
Union	LOCATION
.	O
All	O
3	NUMBER
have	O
been	O
in	DIS
people	O
who	O
had	O
been	O
in	DIS
close	O
contact	O
with	O
bats	VIC
.	O
One	NUMBER
was	O
a	VIC
bat	VIC
handler	O
and	O
other	O
2	DIS
had	O
been	O
bitten	O
-LRB-	O
10-13	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
A	VIC
15-year-old	DURATION
girl	O
died	O
about	DURATION
5	DURATION
weeks	DURATION
after	O
being	O
bitten	O
by	O
a	VIC
bat	VIC
on	O
finger	O
in	DIS
Ukraine	LOCATION
in	DIS
1977	DATE
-LRB-	O
13	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
In	O
Russia	LOCATION
in	DIS
1985	DATE
an	DIS
11-year-old	DURATION
girl	O
died	O
4	DURATION
weeks	DURATION
after	O
being	O
bitten	O
on	O
lower	O
lip	O
by	O
a	VIC
bat	VIC
-LRB-	O
13	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
Also	O
in	DIS
1985	DATE
,	O
a	VIC
30-year-old	DURATION
Finnish	MISC
man	VIC
presented	O
with	O
ascending	O
paralysis	O
and	O
pain	O
in	DIS
arm	O
and	O
neck	O
51	DURATION
days	DURATION
following	O
a	VIC
bat	VIC
bite	O
in	DIS
Finland	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
11	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
He	O
progressed	O
to	O
becoming	O
agitated	O
,	O
with	O
hyperventilation	O
and	O
spasms	O
,	O
and	O
died	O
20	DURATION
days	DURATION
following	O
admission	O
.	O
None	O
of	O
these	O
patients	O
had	O
received	O
specific	O
treatment	O
after	O
their	O
exposure	O
.	O
The	DIS
different	DIS
rabies-like	DIS
viruses	DIS
and	O
bat	VIC
species	VIC
found	O
in	DIS
Europe	LOCATION
distinguish	O
this	O
region	O
from	O
Americas	LOCATION
,	O
where	O
risk	O
of	O
rabies	DIS
following	O
human	O
contact	O
with	O
bats	VIC
is	O
higher	O
-LRB-	O
14	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
Prevention	O
of	O
European	DIS
bat	VIC
lyssavirus	DIS
infection	DIS
in	DIS
humans	DIS
:	O
Bats	O
present	DATE
virtually	O
no	O
risk	O
to	O
general	O
public	O
and	O
are	O
protected	O
by	O
law	O
in	DIS
the	VIC
UK	VIC
.	O
If	O
a	VIC
member	O
of	O
public	O
comes	O
across	O
a	VIC
bat	VIC
,	O
for	O
example	O
because	O
it	O
is	O
injured	O
,	O
they	O
should	O
not	O
touch	O
the	VIC
bat	VIC
but	O
seek	O
help	O
.	O
Only	DIS
licensed	O
or	O
volunteer	O
bat	VIC
handlers	O
should	O
routinely	O
come	O
into	O
contact	O
with	O
bats	VIC
,	O
and	O
they	O
should	O
take	O
suitable	O
precautions	O
,	O
including	O
wearing	O
bite-proof	O
gloves	O
.	O
The	DIS
Department	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
for	O
England	LOCATION
has	O
advised	O
that	O
all	O
bat	VIC
handlers	O
,	O
whether	O
licensed	O
or	O
not	O
,	O
should	O
have	O
pre-exposure	O
immunization	O
against	O
rabies	DIS
-LRB-	O
15	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
Bat	O
handlers	O
should	O
have	O
booster	O
rabies	DIS
vaccination	O
every	SET
3	SET
to	SET
5	SET
years	SET
.	O
Post-exposure	O
prophylaxis	O
:	O
The	DIS
change	O
in	DIS
policy	O
also	O
affects	O
management	O
of	O
close	O
exposures	O
to	O
bats	VIC
in	DIS
the	VIC
UK	VIC
.	O
Prophylaxis	O
for	O
exposure	O
to	O
EBL	DIS
is	O
same	O
as	O
that	O
recommended	O
for	O
other	O
potential	O
rabies	DIS
virus	DIS
exposures	O
and	O
appears	O
to	O
be	O
highly	O
effective	O
-LRB-	O
16	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
Vaccine	O
failures	O
are	O
very	O
rare	O
if	O
an	DIS
appropriate	O
post-exposure	O
regimen	O
is	O
followed	O
-LRB-	O
17	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
Experience	O
has	O
been	O
gained	O
in	DIS
The	DIS
Netherlands	LOCATION
,	O
where	O
EBLs	DIS
are	O
prevalent	O
.	O
There	O
,	O
as	O
in	DIS
the	VIC
UK	VIC
,	O
people	O
who	O
have	O
been	O
bitten	O
by	O
an	DIS
EBL	DIS
virus-positive	O
bat	VIC
are	O
advised	O
to	O
be	O
vaccinated	O
with	O
rabies	DIS
vaccine	O
as	O
for	O
classical	O
-LRB-	O
genotype	O
1	DIS
-RRB-	O
strains	O
.	O
It	O
has	O
been	O
shown	O
that	O
there	O
is	O
cross-immunity	O
between	O
genotype	O
1	DIS
and	O
genotype	O
5	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
EBL	DIS
1	DIS
-RRB-	O
and	O
genotype	O
6	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
EBL	DIS
2	DIS
-RRB-	O
strains	O
-LRB-	O
18	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
,	O
but	O
it	O
is	O
not	O
known	O
whether	O
rabies	DIS
vaccines	O
are	O
completely	O
protective	O
against	O
EBLs	DIS
.	O
Over	O
last	DURATION
2	DIS
decades	DURATION
several	O
hundred	NUMBER
people	O
in	DIS
Netherlands	LOCATION
have	O
been	O
vaccinated	O
with	O
genotype	O
1	DIS
rabies	DIS
virus	DIS
vaccines	O
after	O
being	O
bitten	O
by	O
an	DIS
EBL-positive	O
bat	VIC
,	O
and	O
no	O
EBL	DIS
infection	DIS
has	O
ever	O
been	O
confirmed	O
in	DIS
a	VIC
human	O
being	O
in	DIS
Netherlands	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
WHM	O
van	PERSON
der	PERSON
Poel	PERSON
,	O
personal	O
communication	O
,	O
20	DATE
Nov	DATE
2002	DATE
-RRB-	O
.	O
Anyone	O
who	O
has	O
been	O
scratched	O
or	O
bitten	O
by	O
a	VIC
bat	VIC
,	O
or	O
who	O
has	O
experienced	O
contact	O
between	O
bat	VIC
saliva	O
or	O
neural	O
tissue	O
and	O
their	O
eyes	O
,	O
broken	O
skin	O
,	O
or	O
mucous	O
membrane	O
should	O
,	O
after	O
assessment	O
,	O
be	O
offered	O
post-exposure	O
vaccination	O
as	O
soon	O
as	O
possible	O
after	O
incident	O
.	O
If	O
person	O
is	O
already	O
fully	O
immunised	O
against	O
rabies	DIS
,	O
they	O
should	O
be	O
offered	O
2	DIS
doses	O
of	O
vaccine	O
.	O
If	O
they	O
were	O
previously	DATE
unimmunised	O
or	O
incompletely	O
immunised	O
,	O
they	O
should	O
be	O
offered	O
5	NUMBER
doses	O
of	O
vaccine	O
.	O
For	O
those	O
who	O
were	O
previously	DATE
unimmunised	O
,	O
and	O
who	O
have	O
been	O
bitten	O
by	O
a	VIC
bat	VIC
that	O
is	O
known	O
,	O
or	O
strongly	O
suspected	O
,	O
to	O
be	O
rabid	O
,	O
rabies	DIS
immunoglobulin	O
may	O
be	O
offered	O
in	DIS
addition	O
to	O
a	VIC
full	O
course	O
of	O
vaccine	O
.	O
In	O
view	O
of	O
occasionally	O
prolonged	O
incubation	O
period	O
of	O
rabies	DIS
,	O
post-exposure	O
vaccination	O
should	O
also	O
be	O
offered	O
to	O
any	O
individuals	O
who	O
have	O
been	O
exposed	O
to	O
bats	VIC
as	O
described	O
above	O
at	O
any	O
point	O
in	DIS
last	DATE
year	DATE
if	O
they	O
did	O
not	O
receive	O
post-exposure	O
vaccination	O
at	O
time	DATE
of	O
incident	O
.	O
General	O
background	O
information	O
about	O
bats	VIC
in	DIS
the	VIC
UK	VIC
can	O
be	O
obtained	O
from	O
The	DIS
Bat	ORGANIZATION
Conservation	ORGANIZATION
Trust	ORGANIZATION
website	O
at	O
<	O
http://www.bats.org.uk/bat_info.htm	NUMBER
>	O
.	O
Public	O
health	O
authorities	O
in	DIS
other	O
countries	O
should	O
note	O
change	O
of	O
policy	O
so	O
that	O
returning	O
travellers	O
who	O
report	O
exposure	O
to	O
bats	VIC
in	DIS
the	VIC
UK	VIC
are	O
offered	O
prophylaxis	O
if	O
appropriate	O
.	O
References	O
:	O
-LRB-	O
1	DIS
-RRB-	O
CDSC	O
.	O
Possible	DIS
rabies-like	DIS
infection	DIS
in	DIS
Scotland	LOCATION
.	O
Commun	MISC
Dis	MISC
Rep	MISC
CDR	MISC
Wkly	O
2002	DATE
;	O
12	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
47	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
:	O
news	O
.	O
<	O
http://www.phls.co.uk/publications/cdr/index.html	NUMBER
>	O
-LRB-	O
2	DIS
-RRB-	O
SCIEH	O
.	O
Suspected	DIS
rabies	DIS
case	DIS
in	DIS
Tayside	O
.	O
SCIEH	O
Weekly	SET
Report	O
2002	DATE
;	O
36	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
46	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
:	O
297	NUMBER
.	O
<	O
http://www.show.scot.nhs.uk/scieh/PDF/weekly_report.pdf	O
>	O
-LRB-	O
3	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
PHLS	O
website	O
.	O
Rabies	O
homepage	O
-LSB-	O
online	O
-RSB-	O
-LSB-	O
cited	O
21	DATE
Nov	DATE
2002	DATE
-RSB-	O
-LRB-	O
4	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
DEFRA	O
.	O
Suspected	DIS
case	DIS
of	O
bat	VIC
rabies	DIS
in	DIS
Lancashire	LOCATION
.	O
-LRB-	O
News	O
release	O
389/02	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
London	LOCATION
:	O
DEFRA	LOCATION
,	O
28	DATE
Sep	DATE
2002	DATE
.	O
<	O
http://www.defra.gov.uk/news/2002/020928b.htm	NUMBER
>	O
-LRB-	O
5	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
CDSC	O
.	O
Bat	O
brings	O
rabies	DIS
to	O
Britain	LOCATION
.	O
Commun	O
Dis	O
Rep	O
CDR	O
Wkly	O
1996	DATE
;	O
6	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
24	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
:	O
205	NUMBER
.	O
<	O
http://www.phls.org.uk/publications/cdr/CDR96/cdr2496.pdf	O
>	O
-LRB-	O
6	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
PHLS	O
.	O
A	VIC
case	DIS
of	O
bat	VIC
rabies	DIS
in	DIS
Lancashire	LOCATION
.	O
Commun	MISC
Dis	MISC
Rep	MISC
CDR	MISC
Wkly	O
2002	DATE
;	O
12	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
40	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
:	O
news	O
.	O
<	O
http://www.phls.org.uk/publications/cdr/archive02/News/news4002.html#bats	O
>	O
-LRB-	O
7	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Fooks	ORGANIZATION
AR	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Johnson	PERSON
N.	PERSON
Sporadic	PERSON
case	DIS
of	O
bat	VIC
rabies	DIS
in	DIS
United	LOCATION
Kingdom	LOCATION
.	O
Eurosurveillance	O
Weekly	SET
2002	DATE
;	O
6	NUMBER
:	O
021003	NUMBER
.	O
<	O
http://www.eurosurveillance.org/ew/2002/021003.asp	NUMBER
>	O
-LRB-	O
8	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Whitby	ORGANIZATION
JE	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Johnstone	PERSON
P	O
,	O
Parsons	PERSON
G	O
,	O
King	ORGANIZATION
AA	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Hutson	PERSON
AM	O
.	O
Ten-year	DURATION
survey	O
of	O
British	MISC
bats	VIC
for	O
existence	O
of	O
rabies	DIS
.	O
Vet	O
Rec	O
1996	DATE
;	O
139	NUMBER
:	O
491-3	NUMBER
.	O
-LRB-	O
9	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Danish	ORGANIZATION
Veterinary	ORGANIZATION
Institute	ORGANIZATION
.	O
A	VIC
new	O
case	DIS
of	O
European	DIS
bat	VIC
lyassavirus	O
-LRB-	O
EBL	DIS
-RRB-	O
infection	DIS
in	DIS
Danish	MISC
sheep	O
.	O
Rabies	O
Bulletin	O
Europe	O
2002	DATE
;	O
2	DIS
:	O
15	NUMBER
.	O
<	O
http://www.who-rabies-bulletin.org/q2_2002/contents/4.2.html	NUMBER
>	O
-LRB-	O
10	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Berger	ORGANIZATION
R	ORGANIZATION
.	O
A	VIC
human	O
rabies	DIS
case	DIS
in	DIS
Finland	LOCATION
possibly	O
of	O
bat	VIC
origin	O
.	O
Rabies	O
Bulletin	O
Europe	O
1986	DATE
;	O
4:12	TIME
.	O
-LRB-	O
11	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Lumio	PERSON
J	PERSON
,	O
Hillbom	PERSON
M	O
,	O
Roine	PERSON
R	PERSON
,	O
Ketonen	PERSON
L	PERSON
,	O
Haltia	O
M	O
,	O
Valle	LOCATION
M	O
,	O
et	O
al.	O
.	O
Human	O
rabies	DIS
of	O
bat	VIC
origin	O
in	DIS
Europe	LOCATION
.	O
Lancet	O
1986	DATE
;	O
1	DIS
-LRB-	O
8477	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
:	O
378	NUMBER
.	O
-LRB-	O
12	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Roine	ORGANIZATION
RO	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Hillbom	O
M	O
,	O
Valle	LOCATION
M	O
,	O
Haltia	O
M	O
,	O
Ketonen	PERSON
L	PERSON
,	O
Neuvonen	O
E	O
,	O
et	O
al.	O
.	O
Fatal	O
encephalitis	O
caused	O
by	O
a	VIC
bat-borne	DIS
rabies-related	DIS
virus	DIS
.	O
Brain	O
1988	DATE
;	O
111	NUMBER
:	O
1505	DATE
.	O
-LRB-	O
13	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
World	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
Organization	ORGANIZATION
.	O
Bat	O
rabies	DIS
in	DIS
Union	O
of	O
Soviet	O
Socialist	O
Republics	O
.	O
Rabies	O
Bulletin	O
Europe	O
1987	DATE
;	O
4	NUMBER
:	O
12	NUMBER
.	O
-LRB-	O
14	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Warrell	ORGANIZATION
MJ	ORGANIZATION
.	O
Human	O
deaths	O
from	O
cryptic	O
bat	VIC
rabies	DIS
in	DIS
USA	LOCATION
.	O
Lancet	O
1995	DATE
;	O
346	NUMBER
:	O
65-6	NUMBER
.	O
-LRB-	O
15	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Immunisation	O
against	O
infectious	O
disease	O
,	O
sections	O
27.3	NUMBER
and	O
27.4	NUMBER
.	O
London	LOCATION
:	O
Department	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
,	O
1996	DATE
.	O
<	O
http://www.doh.gov.uk/greenbook/greenbookpdf/chapter-27-layout.pdf	NUMBER
>	O
-LRB-	O
16	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Debbie	PERSON
JG	PERSON
,	O
Trimarchi	PERSON
CV	O
.	O
Prophylaxis	O
for	O
suspected	O
exposure	O
to	O
bat	VIC
rabies	DIS
.	O
Lancet	O
1997	DATE
;	O
350	NUMBER
:	O
1790-1	NUMBER
.	O
-LRB-	O
17	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Anonymous	O
.	O
Rabies	O
vaccine	O
failures	O
.	O
Lancet	O
1988	DATE
:	O
1	DIS
-LRB-	O
8591	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
:	O
917-8	NUMBER
.	O
-LRB-	O
18	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Badrane	O
H	O
,	O
Bahloul	ORGANIZATION
C	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Perrin	PERSON
P	O
,	O
Tordo	PERSON
N.	PERSON
Evidence	PERSON
of	O
two	NUMBER
lyssavirus	DIS
phylogroups	O
with	O
distinct	O
pathogenicity	O
and	O
immunogenicity	O
.	O
J	O
Virol	O
2001	DATE
;	O
75	NUMBER
:	O
3268-76	NUMBER
.	O
Reported	O
by	O
Natasha	PERSON
Crowcroft	PERSON
-LRB-	O
ncrowcroft@phls.org.uk	O
-RRB-	O
,	O
Public	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
Laboratory	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
Communicable	ORGANIZATION
Disease	ORGANIZATION
Surveillance	ORGANIZATION
Centre	ORGANIZATION
,	O
London	LOCATION
,	O
England	LOCATION
Rock	ORGANIZATION
Springs	ORGANIZATION
Run	ORGANIZATION
State	ORGANIZATION
Reserve	ORGANIZATION
-LRB-	O
just	O
north	O
of	O
Orlando	LOCATION
,	O
FL	LOCATION
-RRB-	O
I	O
,	O
along	O
with	O
other	O
park	O
staff	O
completely	O
surveyed	O
a	O
95	NUMBER
acre	O
burn	O
zone	O
for	O
dead	VIC
tortoises	VIC
.	O
Our	O
group	O
of	O
about	O
8	NUMBER
people	O
took	O
2	DURATION
hours	DURATION
surveying	O
the	O
sandhill	O
habitat	O
and	O
found	O
60	NUMBER
dead	VIC
gopher	VIC
tortoises	VIC
.	O
The	O
tortoises	VIC
seem	O
to	O
be	O
virtually	O
extirpated	O
from	O
this	O
area	O
.	O
This	O
zone	O
has	O
been	O
well	O
managed	O
by	O
the	O
park	O
staff	O
and	O
appears	O
to	O
have	O
all	O
the	O
components	O
to	O
support	O
a	O
healthy	O
g.t.	O
population	O
.	O
The	O
tortoises	VIC
were	O
clearly	O
not	O
killed	O
by	O
an	DIS
animal	O
or	O
human	O
.	O
But	O
we	O
have	O
not	O
gotten	O
blood	O
samples	O
from	O
enough	O
tortoises	VIC
in	O
the	O
area	O
to	O
make	O
an	DIS
upper	DIS
respiratory	DIS
tract	DIS
infection	DIS
claim	DIS
as	O
of	O
right	DATE
now	DATE
.	O
Right	DATE
now	DATE
we	O
are	O
surveying	O
a	O
zone	O
that	O
is	O
next	O
to	O
the	O
above	O
mentioned	O
zone	O
.	O
We	O
know	O
there	O
are	O
many	O
dead	VIC
tortoises	VIC
in	O
that	O
area	O
as	O
well	O
.	O
If	O
I	O
had	O
to	O
make	O
an	DIS
estimate	O
I	O
would	O
say	O
there	O
are	O
approximately	VIC
120-140	VIC
dead	VIC
tortoises	VIC
in	O
an	DIS
area	O
of	O
about	O
200	NUMBER
acres	O
.	O
Please	O
call	O
or	O
email	O
if	O
you	O
have	O
witnessed	O
any	O
other	O
die-offs	O
in	O
the	O
Orlando	LOCATION
or	O
surrounding	O
area	O
.	O
--	PERSON
Boyd	PERSON
Blihovde	PERSON
,	O
Park	O
Biologist	O
Wekiva	O
Basin	O
GEOpark	O
1800	DATE
Wekiwa	LOCATION
Circle	LOCATION
Apopka	LOCATION
,	O
Florida	LOCATION
32712	NUMBER
407-884-2006	NUMBER
<boyd.blihovde@dep.state.fl.us>	O
...	O
tg/pg/jw	O
---------------------------------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
Chinese	MISC
scientists	O
have	O
found	O
that	O
the	DIS
coronavirus	DIS
that	O
causes	O
severe	DIS
acute	DIS
respiratory	DIS
syndrome	DIS
-LRB-	O
SARS	DIS
-RRB-	O
is	O
also	O
carried	O
by	O
foxes	VIC
-LSB-	O
domestic	O
?	O
-RSB-	O
cats	VIC
,	O
not	O
just	O
civets	O
,	O
according	O
to	O
Guangzhou	LOCATION
Evening	TIME
Newspaper	O
.	O
Lin	PERSON
Jinyan	PERSON
,	O
leader	O
of	O
a	DIS
SARS	DIS
control	O
prevention	O
research	O
team	O
in	O
south	O
China	LOCATION
's	O
Guangdong	LOCATION
Province	LOCATION
,	O
reported	O
in	O
a	DIS
seminar	O
held	O
in	O
Guangzhou	LOCATION
that	O
other	VIC
wild	VIC
animals	VIC
were	O
also	O
found	O
to	O
carry	O
virus	O
.	O
The	O
team	O
had	O
tested	O
thousands	O
of	O
people	O
-LSB-	O
for	O
-RSB-	O
SARS	DIS
antibodies	O
in	O
16	NUMBER
cities	O
in	O
Guangdong	LOCATION
found	O
that	O
among	O
994	NUMBER
people	O
working	O
in	O
animal	O
markets	O
,	O
10.6	VIC
percent	VIC
carried	O
positive	O
antibodies	O
,	O
among	O
123	NUMBER
civet	VIC
cat	O
husbandry	O
staff	O
,	O
only	O
3.25	VIC
percent	VIC
tested	O
positive	O
.	O
Experts	O
have	O
also	O
tested	O
foxes	VIC
,	O
hedge-shrews	VIC
and	VIC
cats	VIC
collected	O
in	O
province	O
discovered	O
that	O
some	O
carried	O
the	DIS
SARS	DIS
coronavirus	DIS
.	O
On	O
16	DATE
Jan	DATE
2004	DATE
,	O
World	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
Organization	ORGANIZATION
experts	O
claimed	O
that	O
the	DIS
SARS	DIS
coronavirus	DIS
or	O
a	DIS
SARS-like	DIS
coronavirus	DIS
was	O
linked	O
to	O
civet	VIC
cats	VIC
.	O
WHO	O
epidemiologist	O
Robert	PERSON
Breiman	PERSON
said	O
it	O
's	O
possible	O
that	O
other	VIC
animals	VIC
were	O
also	O
involved	O
in	O
spread	O
of	O
SARS	DIS
.	O
-LSB-	O
These	O
observations	O
extend	O
range	O
of	O
animal	O
species	O
known	O
to	O
harbour	O
the	DIS
SARS	DIS
coronavirus	DIS
-LRB-	O
or	O
a	DIS
closely	O
related	O
coronavirus	DIS
-RRB-	O
.	O
The	O
results	O
of	O
human	O
antibody	O
study	O
suggest	O
that	O
transmission	O
of	O
SARS	DIS
coronavirus	DIS
from	O
civets	O
to	O
humans	O
,	O
if	O
it	O
occurs	O
at	O
all	O
,	O
is	O
less	O
efficient	O
than	O
from	O
some	O
other	VIC
animals	VIC
.	O
What	O
is	O
certain	O
is	O
that	O
a	DIS
very	O
large	O
number	O
of	O
civet	VIC
cats	VIC
was	O
destroyed	O
unjustifiably	O
.	O
These	O
data	O
do	O
not	O
establish	O
direction	O
of	O
transmission	O
of	O
infection	O
--	O
from	O
animal	O
to	O
man	O
,	O
or	O
reverse	O
.	O
The	O
origin	O
of	O
the	DIS
SARS	DIS
coronavirus	DIS
remains	O
obscure	O
,	O
it	O
is	O
possible	O
that	O
virus	O
has	O
been	O
present	DATE
in	O
human	O
population	O
for	O
some	O
time	O
,	O
only	O
developing	O
virulence	O
recently	DATE
.	O
-	O
Mod.CP	O
-RSB-	O
-LSB-	O
Thanks	O
to	O
Alfonso	PERSON
Rodriguez	PERSON
,	O
who	O
sent	O
in	O
another	O
version	O
of	O
this	O
article	O
.	O
This	O
report	O
is	O
also	O
interesting	O
in	O
apparently	O
showing	O
a	DIS
significant	O
number	O
of	O
SARS	DIS
survivors	O
in	O
animal	O
handling	O
population	O
.	O
One	NUMBER
might	O
wonder	O
at	O
specificity	O
of	O
antibody	O
test	O
used	O
.	O
-	O
Mod.JW	O
-RSB-	O
---------------------------------------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
According	O
to	O
the	O
data	O
published	O
today	DATE
by	O
the	O
Congolese	ORGANIZATION
Ministry	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
,	O
at	VIC
least	VIC
81	VIC
persons	VIC
have	O
died	O
as	O
a	O
result	O
of	O
the	O
epidemic	O
of	O
Ebola	DIS
hemorrhagic	DIS
fever	DIS
in	O
the	O
Cuvette	LOCATION
Ouest	LOCATION
Region	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
northwest	O
Congo	LOCATION
-RRB-	O
,	O
on	O
the	O
border	O
with	O
Gabon	LOCATION
.	O
The	O
Ministry	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
information	O
bulletin	O
indicates	O
that	O
the	O
district	O
of	O
Kelle	PERSON
,	O
430	NUMBER
miles	O
northwest	O
of	O
Brazzaville	LOCATION
,	O
where	O
the	O
main	O
focus	O
of	O
the	O
epidemic	O
is	O
located	O
,	O
registered	O
72	NUMBER
deaths	O
,	O
while	O
the	O
neighboring	O
district	O
of	O
Mbomo	LOCATION
,	O
almost	O
500	NUMBER
miles	O
further	O
north	O
,	O
reported	O
9	NUMBER
victims	O
since	O
the	O
disease	O
appeared	O
on	O
4	DATE
Jan	DATE
2003	DATE
.	O
In	O
1996	DATE
,	O
a	O
similar	O
epidemic	O
caused	O
the	O
death	O
of	O
hundreds	O
of	O
people	O
in	O
the	O
Democratic	LOCATION
Republic	LOCATION
of	LOCATION
Congo	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
DRC	ORGANIZATION
-RRB-	O
.	O
Shortly	O
before	O
,	O
WHO	ORGANIZATION
spokesperson	O
Fadela	PERSON
Chaib	PERSON
had	O
stated	O
that	O
in	O
Cuvette	PERSON
Ouest	PERSON
,	O
80	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
97	NUMBER
cases	O
of	O
Ebola	DIS
hemorrhagic	DIS
fever	DIS
registered	O
had	O
died	O
.	O
According	O
to	O
the	O
WHO	ORGANIZATION
data	O
,	O
72	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
85	NUMBER
cases	O
registered	O
in	O
Kelle	PERSON
died	O
,	O
as	O
did	O
8	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
12	NUMBER
cases	O
registered	O
in	O
Mbomo	LOCATION
.	O
According	O
to	O
Chaib	PERSON
,	O
local	O
communities	O
have	O
begun	O
to	O
have	O
a	O
better	O
understanding	O
of	O
this	O
highly	O
contagious	O
disease	O
,	O
and	O
have	O
less	O
fear	O
,	O
thanks	O
in	O
part	O
to	O
the	O
medical	O
and	O
expert	O
teams	O
that	O
have	O
arrived	O
and	O
who	O
are	O
instructing	O
them	O
to	O
not	O
eat	O
dead	O
monkeys	O
found	O
in	O
the	O
forest	O
,	O
as	O
well	O
as	O
to	O
change	O
their	O
burial	O
rites	O
.	O
-LSB-	O
The	O
Ministry	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
report	O
increases	O
the	O
number	O
of	O
death	O
reported	O
by	O
WHO	O
by	O
one	NUMBER
.	O
-	O
Mod.CP	O
-RSB-	O
into	O
when	O
they	O
camped	O
out	O
Saturday	DATE
at	O
Dutchman	O
's	O
Grave	LOCATION
Springs	LOCATION
,	O
a	O
remote	O
area	O
northeast	O
of	O
Horseshoe	LOCATION
Lake	LOCATION
.	O
The	O
Mesa	ORGANIZATION
Scouts	ORGANIZATION
had	O
settled	O
in	O
for	O
the	O
night	TIME
after	O
a	O
five-mile	O
hike	O
to	O
the	O
campsite	O
,	O
north	O
of	O
Fountain	LOCATION
Hills	LOCATION
,	O
when	O
Motil	PERSON
,	O
47	NUMBER
,	O
set	O
out	O
to	O
investigate	O
a	O
screeching	O
sound	O
.	O
He	O
soon	O
found	O
himself	O
face	O
to	O
face	O
with	O
a	O
fox	O
.	O
The	O
animal	O
attacked	O
,	O
cutting	O
into	O
Motil	PERSON
's	O
leg	O
.	O
Tests	O
would	O
later	O
confirm	O
his	O
fears	O
:	O
The	O
animal	O
had	O
rabies	DIS
.	O
Motil	PERSON
's	O
case	O
marks	O
the	O
100th	ORDINAL
rabies	DIS
case	O
this	DATE
year	DATE
for	O
Arizona	LOCATION
,	O
the	O
highest	O
number	O
in	O
15	DURATION
years	DURATION
.	O
Of	O
those	O
,	O
there	O
have	O
39	VIC
human	VIC
exposures	VIC
to	O
rabies	DIS
recorded	O
this	DATE
year	DATE
,	O
all	O
of	O
which	O
were	O
treated	O
.	O
Thirty-one	NUMBER
of	O
those	O
cases	O
involved	O
people	O
picking	O
up	O
grounded	O
bats	O
.	O
Mira	PERSON
Leslie	PERSON
,	O
a	O
public	O
health	O
veterinarian	O
with	O
the	O
Arizona	ORGANIZATION
Department	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
Services	ORGANIZATION
,	O
said	O
treatment	O
has	O
improved	O
but	O
doctors	O
still	O
know	O
relatively	O
little	O
about	O
rabies	DIS
.	O
But	O
they	O
say	O
Motil	PERSON
did	O
everything	O
right	O
.	O
The	O
6-foot-7	O
Scout	O
leader	O
moved	O
quickly	O
,	O
striking	O
the	O
animal	O
with	O
his	O
flashlight	O
and	O
pinning	O
the	O
4-foot-long	O
fox	O
to	O
the	O
ground	O
with	O
one	NUMBER
hand	O
while	O
gesturing	O
to	O
the	O
troop	O
for	O
a	O
stick	O
and	O
some	O
rope	O
.	O
He	O
hogtied	O
the	O
gray	O
fox	O
,	O
then	O
tied	O
it	O
to	O
a	O
tree	O
as	O
he	O
went	O
off	O
to	O
bed	O
,	O
wondering	O
if	O
he	O
had	O
been	O
bitten	O
by	O
an	O
animal	O
infected	O
with	O
rabies	DIS
.	O
``	O
After	O
we	O
had	O
tied	O
up	O
the	O
fox	O
,	O
we	O
pulled	O
off	O
my	O
sock	O
-LRB-	O
expecting	O
to	O
see	O
a	O
bite	O
-RRB-	O
and	O
went	O
,	O
`	O
Whew	O
,	O
that	O
was	O
n't	O
much	O
,	O
'	O
''	O
Motil	PERSON
said	O
.	O
``	O
It	O
was	O
n't	O
until	O
later	O
that	O
we	O
discovered	O
the	O
small	O
holes	O
.	O
''	O
The	O
fox	O
died	O
during	O
the	O
night	TIME
.	O
Motil	PERSON
,	O
a	O
lab	O
manager	O
at	O
Phoenix	ORGANIZATION
Children	ORGANIZATION
's	ORGANIZATION
Hospital	ORGANIZATION
,	O
knew	O
speed	O
was	O
a	O
necessity	O
as	O
the	O
presence	O
of	O
rabies	DIS
deteriorates	O
after	O
an	O
animal	O
is	O
dead	O
.	O
So	O
the	O
troop	O
trekked	O
back	O
to	O
the	O
vans	O
for	O
the	O
return	O
trip	O
to	O
the	O
Valley	LOCATION
.	O
State	O
lab	O
technicians	O
began	O
the	O
grisly	O
testing	O
process	O
immediately	O
:	O
The	O
animal	O
is	O
decapitated	O
and	O
a	O
fluorescent	O
solution	O
is	O
spread	O
around	O
on	O
parts	O
of	O
the	O
brain	O
.	O
Areas	O
infected	O
by	O
rabies	DIS
begin	O
to	O
glow	O
bright	O
green	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
fox	O
's	O
tissue	O
lit	O
up	O
like	O
a	O
Christmas	DATE
tree	O
.	O
The	O
Scout	O
leader	O
began	O
treatment	O
for	O
the	O
bite	O
Sunday	DATE
with	O
the	O
first	ORDINAL
of	O
five	NUMBER
shots	O
of	O
serum	O
spread	O
over	O
one	DURATION
month	DURATION
.	O
``	O
He	O
was	O
skilled	O
in	O
the	O
way	O
he	O
handled	O
the	O
fox	O
,	O
''	O
Leslie	PERSON
said	O
of	O
Motil	LOCATION
,	O
a	O
troop	O
leader	O
for	O
4	DURATION
years	DURATION
.	O
``	O
Most	O
people	O
do	O
n't	O
have	O
that	O
.	O
''	O
-LSB-	O
Thanks	O
very	O
much	O
,	O
Phyllis	PERSON
,	O
for	O
sending	O
this	O
to	O
ProMED-mail	O
.	O
The	O
details	O
of	O
how	O
he	O
dealt	O
with	O
the	O
fox	O
bite	O
are	O
impressive	O
,	O
to	O
say	O
the	O
least	O
.	O
Congratulations	O
to	O
the	O
scout	O
leader	O
.	O
What	O
a	O
great	O
example	O
of	O
appropriate	O
action	O
for	O
the	O
kids	O
in	O
his	O
troop	O
.	O
-	O
Mod.PC	O
-RSB-	O
...	O
es	O
----------	NUMBER
.	O
Protecting	O
the	O
United	LOCATION
Kingdom	LOCATION
Blood	O
Supply	O
from	O
Variant	DIS
CJD	DIS
:	O
Donors	O
Who	O
Have	O
Received	O
a	O
Blood	MISC
Transfusion	MISC
Can	MISC
No	MISC
Longer	MISC
Donate	MISC
Blood	MISC
-------------------------------------------------	NUMBER
On	O
Tue	DATE
16	DATE
Mar	DATE
2004	DATE
,	O
the	O
Department	O
of	O
Health	O
in	O
England	LOCATION
announced	O
that	O
people	O
who	O
have	O
received	O
a	O
blood	O
transfusion	O
in	O
the	O
United	LOCATION
Kingdom	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
UK	LOCATION
-RRB-	O
since	O
1	DATE
Jan	DATE
1980	DATE
will	O
no	O
longer	O
be	O
able	O
to	O
donate	O
blood	O
-LRB-	O
1,2	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
This	O
additional	O
donor	O
selection	O
criterion	O
will	O
be	O
implemented	O
by	O
all	O
four	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
UK	LOCATION
Blood	O
Services	O
-LRB-	O
UKBS	O
-RRB-	O
,	O
including	O
the	O
National	ORGANIZATION
Blood	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
on	O
5	DATE
Apr	DATE
2004	DATE
.	O
-LRB-	O
<	O
http://www.blood.co.uk/	NUMBER
>	O
-RRB-	O
This	O
additional	O
precautionary	O
measure	O
to	O
safeguard	O
the	O
blood	O
supply	O
is	O
being	O
taken	O
in	O
the	O
light	O
of	O
the	O
1st	ORDINAL
possible	O
transmission	O
of	O
variant	DIS
Creutzfeldt-Jakob	DIS
disease	DIS
-LSB-	O
abbreviated	O
as	O
CJD	DIS
-LRB-	O
new	DIS
var	DIS
,	O
-RRB-	O
or	O
vCJD	DIS
in	O
ProMED-mail	O
-RSB-	O
by	O
blood	O
transfusion	O
,	O
which	O
was	O
reported	O
in	O
December	DATE
2003	DATE
-LRB-	O
3	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
.	O
The	O
transfusion	O
occurred	O
in	O
1996	DATE
;	O
the	O
blood	O
donor	O
was	O
well	O
at	O
the	O
time	DATE
but	O
developed	O
symptoms	O
of	O
vCJD	DIS
in	O
1999	DATE
and	O
died	O
the	DATE
following	DATE
year	DATE
.	O
The	O
recipient	O
was	O
diagnosed	O
with	O
vCJD	DIS
in	O
2003	DATE
.	O
Since	O
1997	DATE
,	O
in	O
view	O
of	O
the	O
uncertainty	O
as	O
to	O
whether	O
vCJD	DIS
could	O
be	O
transmitted	O
by	O
blood	O
or	O
blood	O
products	O
,	O
the	O
UKBS	ORGANIZATION
have	O
put	O
in	O
place	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
other	O
measures	O
to	O
reduce	O
the	O
risk	O
of	O
a	O
potential	O
onward	O
cycle	O
of	O
transmission	O
:	O
-LRB-	O
1	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Withdrawal	O
and	O
recall	O
of	O
any	O
blood	O
components	O
,	O
plasma	O
derivatives	O
,	O
or	O
tissues	O
obtained	O
from	O
any	O
individual	O
who	O
later	O
develops	O
vCJD	DIS
-LRB-	O
December	DATE
1997	DATE
-RRB-	O
;	O
-LRB-	O
2	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Importation	O
of	O
plasma	O
from	O
the	O
US	LOCATION
for	O
fractionation	O
to	O
manufacture	O
plasma	O
derivatives	O
-LRB-	O
announced	O
May	DATE
1998	DATE
,	O
implemented	O
October	DATE
1999	DATE
-RRB-	O
;	O
-LRB-	O
3	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Leucodepletion	O
-LRB-	O
removal	O
of	O
white	O
blood	O
cells	O
-RRB-	O
of	O
all	O
blood	O
components	O
-LRB-	O
announced	O
July	DATE
1998	DATE
,	O
implemented	O
Autumn	DATE
1999	DATE
-RRB-	O
;	O
-LRB-	O
4	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Importation	O
of	O
fresh	O
frozen	O
plasma	O
from	O
the	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
for	O
patients	O
born	O
on	O
or	O
after	O
1	DATE
Jan	DATE
1996	DATE
-LRB-	O
announced	O
August	DATE
2002	DATE
,	O
to	O
be	O
implemented	O
spring	DATE
2004	DATE
-RRB-	O
;	O
-LRB-	O
5	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Promotion	O
of	O
appropriate	O
use	O
of	O
blood	O
and	O
tissues	O
and	O
alternatives	O
throughout	O
the	O
National	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
-LRB-	O
NHS	ORGANIZATION
-RRB-	O
.	O
This	O
is	O
a	O
highly	O
precautionary	O
approach	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
benefit	O
of	O
receiving	O
a	O
blood	O
transfusion	O
when	O
needed	O
far	O
outweighs	O
any	O
possible	O
risk	O
of	O
contracting	O
vCJD	DIS
.	O
To	O
date	O
there	O
has	O
been	O
only	O
one	NUMBER
possible	O
case	O
of	O
vCJD	DIS
being	O
transmitted	O
by	O
blood	O
,	O
yet	O
the	O
UKBS	O
issue	O
over	O
2.5	NUMBER
million	NUMBER
units	O
of	O
blood	O
every	SET
year	SET
.	O
As	O
of	O
1	DATE
Mar	DATE
2004	DATE
there	O
have	O
been	O
146	NUMBER
definite	O
and	O
probable	O
cases	VIC
of	O
vCJD	DIS
in	O
the	O
UK	LOCATION
,	O
one	NUMBER
case	O
each	O
in	O
the	O
Republic	LOCATION
of	LOCATION
Ireland	LOCATION
,	O
Italy	LOCATION
,	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
,	O
Canada	LOCATION
,	O
and	O
Hong	LOCATION
Kong	LOCATION
,	O
and	O
6	VIC
cases	VIC
in	O
France	LOCATION
.	O
The	O
eventual	O
number	O
of	O
individuals	O
within	O
the	O
UK	LOCATION
population	O
likely	O
to	O
develop	O
vCJD	DIS
remains	O
uncertain	O
;	O
estimates	O
range	O
from	O
the	O
current	DATE
numbers	O
up	O
to	O
540	NUMBER
.	O
It	O
is	O
not	O
known	O
how	O
many	O
current	DATE
or	O
past	DATE
blood	O
or	O
tissue	O
donors	O
may	O
develop	O
vCJD	DIS
in	O
the	DATE
future	DATE
.	O
Further	O
information	O
and	O
advice	O
to	O
blood	O
donors	O
and	O
members	O
of	O
the	O
public	O
who	O
are	O
concerned	O
about	O
the	O
risk	O
of	O
contracting	O
vCJD	DIS
from	O
a	O
blood	O
transfusion	O
are	O
being	O
offered	O
via	O
the	O
NHS	ORGANIZATION
Direct	O
service	O
-LRB-	O
<	O
http://www.nhsdirect.nhs.uk/	NUMBER
>	O
-RRB-	O
.	O
-LSB-	O
Byline	O
:	O
Nicky	PERSON
Connor	PERSON
-LRB-	O
<nicky.connor@hpa.org.uk>	O
-RRB-	O
and	O
Helen	PERSON
Janecek	PERSON
,	O
Health	ORGANIZATION
Protection	ORGANIZATION
Agency	ORGANIZATION
Communicable	ORGANIZATION
Disease	ORGANIZATION
Surveillance	ORGANIZATION
Centre	ORGANIZATION
,	O
London	LOCATION
,	O
England	LOCATION
-RSB-	O
-LRB-	O
1	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Department	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
.	O
Further	O
precautions	O
to	O
protect	O
blood	O
supply	O
.	O
Press	O
release	O
2004/0104	NUMBER
,	O
16	DATE
Mar	DATE
2004	DATE
.	O
-LRB-	O
<	O
http://www.dh.gov.uk/PublicationsAndStatistics/PressReleases/PressReleasesNotices/fs/en?CONTENT_ID=4076608&chk=MTwE%2Bl	O
>	O
-RRB-	O
-LRB-	O
2	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Reid	PERSON
J.	O
Developments	O
in	O
CJD	DIS
.	O
House	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Commons	ORGANIZATION
Debate	ORGANIZATION
-LRB-	O
Hansard	PERSON
-RRB-	O
2003-04	DATE
;	O
419	NUMBER
:	O
March	DATE
16	DATE
col	O
157	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
<	O
http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.co.uk/pa/cm200304/cmhansrd/cm040316/debtext/40316-05_head0	NUMBER
>	O
-RRB-	O
-LRB-	O
3	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Llewelyn	ORGANIZATION
CA	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Hewitt	ORGANIZATION
PE	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Knight	ORGANIZATION
RS	ORGANIZATION
,	O
Amar	PERSON
K	PERSON
,	O
Cousens	PERSON
S	O
,	O
Mackenzie	PERSON
J	PERSON
,	O
et	O
al.	O
.	O
Possible	O
transmission	O
of	O
variant	DIS
Creutzfeldt-Jakob	DIS
disease	DIS
by	O
blood	O
transfusion	O
.	O
Lancet	O
2004	DATE
;	O
363:417	NUMBER
-21	NUMBER
.	O
outbreak	O
affecting	O
Pohnpei	LOCATION
State	LOCATION
in	O
the	O
FSM	ORGANIZATION
is	O
posted	O
on	O
behalf	O
of	O
the	O
FSM	ORGANIZATION
Department	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
.	O
Many	O
thanks	O
to	O
our	O
PPHSN	O
colleagues	O
,	O
especially	O
to	O
Dr	O
Tom	PERSON
Kiedrzynski	PERSON
and	O
Martyn	PERSON
Kirk	PERSON
who	O
jointly	O
produced	O
this	O
summary	O
.	O
Tom	PERSON
-LRB-	O
SPC	O
-RRB-	O
,	O
Martyn	PERSON
-LRB-	O
WHO	O
ST	O
Consultant	O
-RRB-	O
and	O
Dr.	O
Iris	PERSON
Wainiqolo	PERSON
-LRB-	O
Fiji	ORGANIZATION
School	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Medicine	ORGANIZATION
-RRB-	O
went	O
on	O
June	DATE
17	DATE
to	O
Pohnpei	LOCATION
,	O
upon	O
request	O
by	O
the	O
FSM	ORGANIZATION
authorities	O
,	O
on	O
behalf	O
of	O
the	O
Coordinating	ORGANIZATION
Body	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
the	ORGANIZATION
Pacific	ORGANIZATION
Public	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
Surveillance	ORGANIZATION
Network	ORGANIZATION
,	O
in	O
order	O
to	O
shoulder	O
the	O
local	O
outbreak	O
investigation	O
and	O
control	O
team	O
.	O
Many	O
thanks	O
also	O
to	O
Dr.	O
Eliaser	PERSON
Johnson	PERSON
and	O
Amato	PERSON
Elymore	PERSON
from	O
Pohnpei	LOCATION
State	LOCATION
and	O
FSM	ORGANIZATION
Federal	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
authorities	O
.	O
All	O
data	O
provided	O
by	O
the	O
Medical	ORGANIZATION
Records	ORGANIZATION
Department	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Pohnpei	ORGANIZATION
Hospital	ORGANIZATION
.	O
Du	PERSON
to	O
the	O
limitations	O
inherent	O
to	O
the	O
.	O
TXT	O
format	O
of	O
PACNET	O
messages	O
,	O
graphs	O
and	O
tables	O
are	O
n't	O
available	O
in	O
this	O
messages	O
.	O
However	O
,	O
a	O
full	O
version	O
of	O
the	O
outbreak	O
summary	O
and	O
update	O
will	O
be	O
available	O
on	O
the	O
SPC	ORGANIZATION
web-site	O
within	O
the	DURATION
next	DURATION
24	DURATION
hours	DURATION
-LRB-	O
see	O
URL	O
address	O
below	O
--	O
YS	O
-RSB-	O
*****	NUMBER
Cholera	DIS
outbreak	O
in	O
Pohnpei-descriptive	MISC
data	O
update	O
Pacific	ORGANIZATION
Public	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
Surveillance	ORGANIZATION
Network	ORGANIZATION
28	DATE
Jun	DATE
2000	DATE
1	DATE
.	O
Introduction	O
This	O
brief	O
update	O
describes	O
the	O
outbreak	O
of	O
cholera	O
on	O
Pohnpei	LOCATION
island	O
that	O
public	O
health	O
authorities	O
recognised	O
on	O
17	DATE
Apr	DATE
2000	DATE
.	O
It	O
has	O
been	O
compiled	O
from	O
inpatient	O
and	O
outpatient	O
data	O
from	O
the	O
Pohnpei	LOCATION
Hospital	LOCATION
,	O
and	O
community-based	O
dispensaries	O
.	O
Up	O
to	O
26	DATE
Jun	DATE
2000	DATE
,	O
there	O
have	O
been	O
1596	DATE
cases	VIC
of	O
acute	O
watery	O
diarrhoea	O
reported	O
since	O
the	O
beginning	O
of	O
the	O
outbreak	O
,	O
which	O
includes	O
cases	VIC
less	DURATION
than	DURATION
5	DURATION
years	DURATION
of	O
age	O
and	O
many	O
for	O
which	O
age	O
was	O
not	O
determined	O
.	O
There	O
have	O
been	O
9	NUMBER
deaths	O
reported	O
in	O
association	O
with	O
the	O
outbreak	O
.	O
The	O
Pohnpei	ORGANIZATION
Hospital	ORGANIZATION
Laboratory	ORGANIZATION
isolated	O
_	NUMBER
Vibrio	O
cholerae	DIS
_	O
,	O
as	O
the	O
cause	O
of	O
this	O
outbreak	O
and	O
the	O
serotype	O
has	O
been	O
confirmed	O
as	O
serotype	O
Ogawa	PERSON
.	O
The	O
biotype	O
is	O
not	O
yet	O
established	O
.	O
There	O
have	O
been	O
954	VIC
cases	VIC
of	O
suspected	O
cholera	O
that	O
meet	O
the	O
World	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
Organization	ORGANIZATION
case	O
definition	O
-LRB-	O
see	O
Note	O
1	NUMBER
below	O
-RRB-	O
.	O
These	O
cases	VIC
were	O
reported	O
from	O
the	O
inpatients	O
,	O
outpatients	O
and	O
emergency	O
departments	O
of	O
the	O
Pohnpei	LOCATION
hospital	O
,	O
and	O
from	O
community-based	O
dispensaries	O
.	O
The	O
first	ORDINAL
individual	O
cases	VIC
were	O
noted	O
in	O
the	O
municipality	O
of	O
Kolonia	LOCATION
,	O
before	O
spreading	O
to	O
Kitti	PERSON
.	O
The	O
outbreak	O
then	O
appears	O
to	O
have	O
spread	O
in	O
a	O
clockwise	O
manner	O
around	O
the	O
island	O
from	O
Kitti	PERSON
.	O
The	O
outbreak	O
is	O
consistent	O
with	O
an	O
initial	O
point-source	O
outbreak	O
at	O
a	O
large	O
funeral	O
in	O
Kitti	PERSON
.	O
This	O
appears	O
to	O
have	O
been	O
followed	O
by	O
a	O
mixture	O
of	O
other	O
point-source	O
outbreaks	O
and	O
transmission	O
from	O
person-to-person	O
.	O
The	O
municipalities	O
of	O
Kitti	PERSON
,	O
Uh	O
and	O
Sokehs	PERSON
had	O
the	O
highest	O
rates	O
of	O
presentation	O
to	O
inpatient	O
or	O
outpatient	O
departments	O
.	O
The	O
highest	O
rates	O
were	O
in	O
males	O
and	O
females	O
in	O
the	O
65-74	NUMBER
year	DURATION
age	O
group	O
.	O
2	NUMBER
.	O
Admissions	O
Data	O
Up	O
to	O
27	DATE
Jun	DATE
2000	DATE
,	O
there	O
were	O
399	NUMBER
admissions	O
for	O
acute	O
watery	O
diarrhoea	O
to	O
the	O
Pohnpei	LOCATION
hospital	O
.	O
Three	NUMBER
hundred	NUMBER
and	NUMBER
sixty	NUMBER
eight	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
92	PERCENT
%	PERCENT
-RRB-	O
-LSB-	O
of	O
the	O
-RSB-	O
cases	VIC
met	O
the	O
WHO	ORGANIZATION
case	O
definition	O
for	O
suspected	O
cholera	O
.	O
The	O
median	O
length	O
of	O
stay	O
in	O
hospital	O
for	O
suspected	O
cholera	O
cases	VIC
was	O
2	DURATION
days	DURATION
-LRB-	O
range	O
0-8	NUMBER
days	DURATION
-RRB-	O
,	O
and	O
44	PERCENT
%	PERCENT
of	O
cases	VIC
were	O
male	O
.	O
Adults	O
were	O
more	O
commonly	O
infected	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
rates	O
of	O
suspected	O
cholera	O
showed	O
a	O
bimodal	O
distribution	O
.	O
The	O
highest	O
rates	O
were	O
in	O
males	O
aged	O
between	O
65-74	NUMBER
years	DURATION
,	O
females	O
75	DURATION
years	DURATION
or	O
greater	O
,	O
and	O
in	O
females	O
between	O
20-24	NUMBER
years	DURATION
old	O
.	O
3	NUMBER
.	O
Outpatients	O
and	O
Emergency	O
presentations	O
Up	O
to	O
27	DATE
Jun	DATE
2000	DATE
,	O
there	O
were	O
777	NUMBER
presentations	O
for	O
acute	O
watery	O
diarrhoea	O
to	O
the	O
Pohnpei	LOCATION
Hospital	LOCATION
outpatient	O
and	O
emergency	O
departments	O
since	O
17	DATE
Apr	DATE
2000	DATE
.	O
Six	NUMBER
hundred	NUMBER
and	NUMBER
twenty	NUMBER
five	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
80	PERCENT
%	PERCENT
-RRB-	O
-LSB-	O
of	O
the	O
-RSB-	O
cases	VIC
met	O
the	O
WHO	ORGANIZATION
definition	O
for	O
suspected	O
cholera	O
,	O
while	O
119	NUMBER
cases	VIC
were	O
less	DURATION
than	DURATION
5	DURATION
years	DURATION
of	O
age	O
,	O
and	O
no	O
age	O
was	O
available	O
for	O
33	NUMBER
cases	VIC
.	O
Fifty	PERCENT
percent	PERCENT
of	O
cases	VIC
of	O
suspected	O
cholera	O
were	O
male	O
.	O
4	NUMBER
.	O
Limitations	O
The	O
inpatients	O
data	O
are	O
the	O
most	O
reliable	O
of	O
the	O
3	NUMBER
possible	O
data	O
sources	O
and	O
were	O
the	O
most	O
complete	O
.	O
There	O
are	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
limitations	O
that	O
must	O
be	O
considered	O
in	O
the	O
interpretation	O
of	O
these	O
data	O
,	O
particularly	O
for	O
outpatients	O
and	O
emergency	O
departments	O
,	O
including	O
:	O
*	O
age	O
&	O
sex	O
was	O
not	O
available	O
for	O
many	O
outpatients	O
*	O
patients	O
may	O
have	O
presented	O
more	O
than	O
once	DATE
for	O
the	O
same	O
episode	O
*	O
the	O
place	O
of	O
residence	O
may	O
be	O
inaccurate	O
*	O
population	O
data	O
used	O
for	O
calculating	O
rates	O
were	O
from	O
the	O
1994	DATE
census	O
*	O
the	O
case	O
definition	O
for	O
suspected	O
cholera	O
was	O
not	O
rigorously	O
applied	O
*	O
there	O
may	O
be	O
errors	O
due	O
to	O
recording	O
,	O
or	O
data	O
entry	O
Note	O
1	NUMBER
:	O
The	O
World	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
Organization	ORGANIZATION
guidelines	O
for	O
cholera	O
control	O
indicate	O
that	O
for	O
surveillance	O
purposes	O
,	O
the	O
case	O
definition	O
for	O
suspected	O
cholera	O
in	O
an	O
epidemic	O
situation	O
should	O
be	O
a	O
person	O
5	DURATION
years	DURATION
of	O
age	O
or	O
greater	O
develops	O
acute	O
watery	O
diarrhoea	O
.	O
Pohnpei	LOCATION
Cholera	DIS
Outbreak	O
,	O
29	DATE
Jun	DATE
2000	DATE
Produced	O
by	O
:	O
T.	ORGANIZATION
Kiedrzynski	ORGANIZATION
&	ORGANIZATION
M.	ORGANIZATION
Kirk	ORGANIZATION
Data	ORGANIZATION
provided	O
by	O
Medical	ORGANIZATION
Records	ORGANIZATION
Department	ORGANIZATION
Pohnpei	ORGANIZATION
Hospital	ORGANIZATION
Contact	ORGANIZATION
persons	O
:	O
Dr.	O
Yvan	PERSON
Souares	PERSON
<yvans@spc.int>	O
Dr.	O
Tom	PERSON
Kiedrzynski	PERSON
<tomk@spc.int>	O
Mrs.	O
Elise	PERSON
Benyon	PERSON
<eliseb@spc.int>	O
Mina	PERSON
Vilayleck	PERSON
<minav@spc.int>	O
Ginette	PERSON
Soehadi	PERSON
<ginettes@spc.int>	O
...	O
chc/jw/es	O
it	O
was	O
in	O
the	O
municipality	O
of	O
Breves	LOCATION
,	O
on	O
Marajo	LOCATION
Island	LOCATION
in	O
Para	LOCATION
state	O
,	O
where	O
there	O
was	O
an	O
outbreak	O
in	O
1998-99	DATE
.	O
During	O
the	O
case	O
investigation	O
,	O
dead	O
monkeys	O
&	O
sloths	O
were	O
found	O
near	O
the	O
probable	O
focus	O
of	O
infection	O
.	O
In	O
Amazonas	LOCATION
state	O
also	O
,	O
there	O
have	O
been	O
reports	O
of	O
dead	O
sloths	O
in	O
places	O
where	O
human	O
cases	VIC
occur	O
.	O
In	O
2002	DATE
the	O
total	O
is	O
already	O
6	VIC
cases	VIC
&	O
2	NUMBER
deaths	O
-LRB-	O
case	O
fatality	O
rate	O
of	O
33	PERCENT
%	PERCENT
-RRB-	O
.	O
-LSB-	O
As	O
far	O
back	O
as	O
the	DATE
1930s	DATE
,	O
Fred	PERSON
Soper	PERSON
&	O
other	O
researchers	O
suspected	O
the	O
sloth	O
to	O
be	O
a	O
reservoir	O
of	O
sylvan	DIS
YF	DIS
.	O
-	O
Mod.LJS	O
-RSB-	O
-----------------------------------------------------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
The	O
Rukhi-Natsuluku	MISC
section	O
of	O
Zugdidi	LOCATION
District	O
-LRB-	O
on	O
the	O
Abkhaz	MISC
border	O
-RRB-	O
has	O
been	O
placed	O
under	O
quarantine	O
after	O
several	VIC
cases	VIC
of	O
human	DIS
anthrax	DIS
were	O
recorded	O
in	O
the	O
area	O
.	O
The	O
4	VIC
residents	VIC
of	O
the	O
village	O
of	O
Rukhi	LOCATION
who	O
have	O
contracted	O
the	O
disease	O
are	O
being	O
treated	O
in	O
hospital	O
in	O
Zugdidi	LOCATION
,	O
while	O
30	NUMBER
others	O
are	O
under	O
medical	O
observation	O
.	O
The	O
authorities	O
of	O
the	O
self-declared	O
republic	O
of	O
Abkhazia	LOCATION
officially	O
announced	O
today	DATE
that	O
they	O
had	O
closed	O
the	O
Inguri	LOCATION
bridge	O
-LRB-	O
linking	O
Abkhazia	LOCATION
with	O
the	O
rest	O
of	O
Georgia	LOCATION
-RRB-	O
yesterday	DATE
in	O
order	O
to	O
prevent	O
the	O
spread	O
of	O
anthrax	DIS
.	O
-LSB-	O
Further	O
details	O
are	O
being	O
sought	O
.	O
-	O
Mod.MHJ	O
-RSB-	O
...	O
jw/mhj/pg	O
/	O
es	O
------------------------------------------------------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
The	O
following	O
figures	O
are	O
reproduced	O
from	O
the	O
Resumen	MISC
Epidemiologica	MISC
accompanying	O
the	O
Maps	O
of	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
Virus	LOCATION
Activity	LOCATION
in	O
Mexico	LOCATION
As	O
of	O
Mon	DATE
6	DATE
Oct	DATE
2003	DATE
,	O
a	O
total	O
of	O
481	NUMBER
individuals	O
resident	O
in	O
20	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
32	NUMBER
states	O
have	O
been	O
tested	O
for	O
evidence	O
of	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus	DIS
infection	DIS
:	O
477	NUMBER
were	O
seronegative	O
and	O
asymptomatic	O
and	O
4	VIC
were	O
classified	O
as	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus-positive	VIC
:	O
3	NUMBER
in	O
the	O
state	O
of	O
Chihuahua	LOCATION
and	O
one	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
confirmed	O
by	O
RT-PCR	O
-RRB-	O
in	O
the	O
state	O
of	O
Sonora	LOCATION
.	O
-LSB-	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus-positive	VIC
cases	VIC
were	O
not	O
reported	O
among	O
the	O
452	NUMBER
individuals	O
tested	O
in	O
the	O
data	O
reproduced	O
in	O
the	O
previous	O
ProMED-mail	O
update	O
dated	O
24	DATE
Sep	DATE
2003	DATE
.	O
-	O
Mod.CP	O
-RSB-	O
As	O
of	O
Mon	DATE
6	DATE
Oct	DATE
2003	DATE
,	O
a	O
total	O
of	O
4472	NUMBER
horses	O
from	O
20	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
32	NUMBER
states	O
have	O
been	O
tested	O
for	O
evidence	O
of	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus	DIS
infection	DIS
.	O
Of	O
these	O
animals	VIC
1453	VIC
were	O
seropositive	VIC
and	O
3018	DATE
seronegative	O
.	O
All	O
these	O
animals	VIC
were	O
asymptomatic	O
.	O
In	O
addition	O
one	NUMBER
animal	O
in	O
the	O
state	O
of	O
Nuevo	LOCATION
Leon	LOCATION
,	O
which	O
had	O
the	O
2nd	ORDINAL
highest	O
incidence	O
of	O
seropositive	VIC
animals	VIC
,	O
was	O
symptomatic	O
and	O
died	O
.	O
-LSB-	O
The	O
number	O
of	O
fatal	O
cases	VIC
is	O
unchanged	O
since	O
24	DATE
Sep	DATE
2003	DATE
.	O
-	O
Mod.CP	O
-RSB-	O
As	O
of	O
Mon	DATE
6	DATE
Oct	DATE
2003	DATE
,	O
a	O
total	O
of	O
17	NUMBER
168	NUMBER
birds	VIC
from	O
8	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
32	NUMBER
states	O
have	O
been	O
tested	O
for	O
evidence	O
of	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus	DIS
infection	DIS
.	O
Of	O
these	O
birds	VIC
63	VIC
were	O
seropositive	VIC
-LRB-	O
and	O
considered	O
to	O
be	O
asymptomatic	O
-RRB-	O
and	O
17	NUMBER
103	NUMBER
were	O
seronegative	O
.	O
In	O
addition	O
2	VIC
dead	VIC
birds	VIC
were	O
seropositive	VIC
.	O
-LSB-	O
The	O
number	O
of	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus-positive	VIC
birds	VIC
is	O
unchanged	O
since	O
24	DATE
Sep	DATE
2003	DATE
.	O
N.B.	O
.	O
The	O
total	O
for	O
seronegative	O
birds	VIC
given	O
in	O
the	O
original	O
table	O
is	O
incorrect	O
in	O
that	O
it	O
omits	O
data	O
for	O
the	O
state	O
of	O
Chihuahua	LOCATION
.	O
-	O
Mod.CP	O
-RSB-	O
-LSB-	O
These	O
new	O
data	O
report	O
the	O
1st	ORDINAL
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus-positive	VIC
human	O
cases	VIC
in	O
Mexico	LOCATION
.	O
Overall	O
the	O
data	O
are	O
strikingly	O
different	O
from	O
those	O
recorded	O
in	O
North	LOCATION
America	LOCATION
with	O
regard	O
to	O
the	O
lower	O
incidence	O
of	O
disease	O
and	O
mortality	O
in	O
Mexico	LOCATION
in	O
the	O
case	O
of	O
animals	VIC
that	O
have	O
tested	O
seropositive	VIC
for	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus	DIS
infection	DIS
.	O
As	O
commented	O
previously	DATE
,	O
this	O
situation	O
raises	O
questions	O
about	O
the	O
possible	O
existence	O
of	O
cross-reactivity	O
as	O
a	O
consequence	O
of	O
infection	DIS
with	O
other	O
related	O
flaviviruses	O
,	O
both	O
in	O
terms	O
of	O
conferring	O
protection	O
and	O
generating	O
false	O
positivity	O
.	O
Further	O
information	O
is	O
awaited	O
with	O
interest	O
.	O
-	O
Mod.CP	O
-RSB-	O
so-called	DIS
``	O
mad	O
cow	DIS
''	O
disease	DIS
-LRB-	O
Bovine	DIS
Spongiform	DIS
Encephalopathy	DIS
,	O
BSE	DIS
-RRB-	O
in	O
a	O
cow	DIS
imported	O
from	O
Denmark	LOCATION
,	O
the	O
Danish	ORGANIZATION
Veterinary	ORGANIZATION
and	ORGANIZATION
Food	ORGANIZATION
Administration	ORGANIZATION
said	O
in	O
a	O
statement	O
Wednesday	DATE
.	O
Although	O
it	O
could	O
not	O
be	O
ruled	O
out	O
the	O
cow	DIS
had	O
caught	O
BSE	DIS
before	O
it	O
left	O
Denmark	LOCATION
,	O
the	O
case	O
did	O
not	O
constitute	O
a	O
risk	O
to	O
Food	O
safety	O
there	O
,	O
said	O
the	O
organization	O
.	O
The	O
cow	DIS
was	O
born	O
in	O
Nordvestjylland	LOCATION
,	O
Denmark	LOCATION
in	O
March	DATE
1992	DATE
and	O
was	O
exported	O
to	O
Portugal	LOCATION
in	O
October	DATE
1994	DATE
from	O
a	O
herd	O
of	O
only	O
16	NUMBER
,	O
none	O
of	O
which	O
was	O
still	O
in	O
Denmark	LOCATION
.	O
While	O
Portugal	LOCATION
has	O
reported	O
13	VIC
new	VIC
cases	VIC
of	O
BSE	DIS
so	O
far	O
this	DATE
year	DATE
and	O
registered	O
170	VIC
cases	VIC
in	O
1999	DATE
,	O
the	O
first	ORDINAL
case	O
of	O
BSE	DIS
in	O
a	O
native	O
Danish	MISC
cattle	O
herd	O
was	O
announced	O
in	O
late	DATE
February	DATE
.	O
A	O
number	O
of	O
countries	O
immediately	O
announced	O
bans	O
on	O
Danish	MISC
beef	O
and	O
Denmark	LOCATION
pulled	O
beef	O
products	O
from	O
its	O
shelves	O
.	O
The	O
Danish	MISC
government	O
admitted	O
March	DATE
1	DATE
it	O
had	O
failed	O
to	O
follow	O
EU	ORGANIZATION
guidelines	O
fast	O
enough	O
to	O
prevent	O
the	O
first	ORDINAL
case	O
.	O
Denmark	LOCATION
had	O
previously	DATE
been	O
criticized	O
by	O
the	O
European	LOCATION
Union	LOCATION
for	O
acting	O
half-heartedly	O
on	O
recommendations	O
to	O
prevent	O
BSE	DIS
,	O
with	O
the	O
government	O
proving	O
unwilling	O
to	O
test	O
dead	O
or	O
sick	O
animals	O
,	O
or	O
introduce	O
new	VIC
methods	O
in	O
abattoirs	O
.	O
Until	O
this	DATE
year	DATE
,	O
Denmark	LOCATION
believed	O
its	O
cattle	O
were	O
free	O
from	O
BSE	DIS
,	O
the	O
only	O
previous	O
case	O
having	O
occurred	O
in	O
1992	DATE
--	O
an	O
import	O
from	O
Scotland	LOCATION
aroused	O
little	O
domestic	O
concern	O
.	O
Denmark	LOCATION
has	O
two	NUMBER
million	NUMBER
head	O
of	O
cattle	O
.	O
--	O
Terry	PERSON
S.	PERSON
Singeltary	PERSON
Sr.flounder@wt.net.......................tg	O
/	O
ds	O
--	O
-----------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
The	DIS
influenza	DIS
B	DIS
virus	DIS
has	O
been	O
found	O
in	O
animals	O
for	O
first	ORDINAL
time	O
,	O
with	O
scientists	O
who	O
made	O
discovery	O
saying	O
it	O
``	O
may	O
pose	O
a	O
direct	O
threat	O
to	O
humans	O
''	O
.	O
The	DIS
virus	DIS
was	O
found	O
in	O
up	O
to	O
2	PERCENT
percent	PERCENT
of	O
seals	VIC
on	O
the	VIC
Dutch	VIC
coast	O
in	O
1999	DATE
and	O
was	O
identical	O
to	O
virus	DIS
prevalent	O
in	O
humans	O
in	O
Netherlands	LOCATION
in	O
1995	DATE
.	O
The	DIS
virus	DIS
is	O
being	O
harbored	O
unchanged	O
by	O
the	VIC
seal	VIC
.	O
Since	O
human	O
immune	O
response	O
to	O
a	O
particular	O
virus	DIS
strain	O
fades	O
with	O
time	O
,	O
any	O
later	O
reintroduction	O
of	O
that	O
strain	O
might	O
have	O
a	O
serious	O
impact	O
.	O
According	O
to	O
team	O
leader	O
Professor	O
Albert	PERSON
Osterhaus	PERSON
,	O
from	O
National	ORGANIZATION
Influenza	ORGANIZATION
Center	ORGANIZATION
at	O
Erasmus	ORGANIZATION
University	ORGANIZATION
,	O
``	O
My	O
message	O
is	O
if	O
you	O
find	O
these	O
animals	O
at	O
beach	O
,	O
just	O
do	O
n't	O
touch	O
them	O
.	O
Stay	O
away	O
and	O
wait	O
until	O
a	O
professional	O
comes	O
.	O
''	O
There	O
are	O
3	NUMBER
types	O
of	O
influenza	DIS
virus	DIS
,	O
A	O
,	O
B	DIS
and	O
C	O
.	O
The	DIS
A	O
type	O
is	O
harbored	O
in	O
birds	O
and	O
also	O
infects	O
humans	O
.	O
It	O
has	O
been	O
responsible	O
for	O
last	DATE
century	DATE
's	O
major	O
pandemics	O
.	O
Until	O
now	DATE
,	O
B	DIS
type	O
was	O
thought	O
to	O
be	O
an	O
exclusively	O
human	O
disease	O
.	O
Dr	O
Alan	PERSON
Hay	PERSON
,	O
Head	O
of	O
WHO	ORGANIZATION
Influenza	ORGANIZATION
Center	ORGANIZATION
at	O
UK	ORGANIZATION
National	ORGANIZATION
Institute	ORGANIZATION
for	ORGANIZATION
Medical	ORGANIZATION
Research	ORGANIZATION
said	O
:	O
``	O
The	DIS
idea	O
of	O
an	O
animal	O
reservoir	O
would	O
be	O
controversial	O
.	O
''	O
Animal	O
reservoirs	O
are	O
important	O
because	O
they	O
harbor	O
viruses	O
,	O
allowing	O
infections	O
to	O
resurface	O
after	O
quiet	O
periods	O
.	O
They	O
can	O
allow	O
viruses	O
to	O
mutate	O
and	O
become	O
more	O
virulent	O
.	O
This	O
had	O
not	O
happened	O
in	O
the	VIC
Dutch	VIC
seals	VIC
.	O
The	DIS
virus	DIS
had	O
remained	O
same	O
for	O
4	DURATION
years	DURATION
.	O
But	O
human	O
virus	DIS
,	O
and	O
human	O
immune	O
response	O
,	O
changes	O
every	SET
year	SET
.	O
If	O
old	O
virus	DIS
resurfaced	O
at	O
a	O
later	O
date	O
,	O
it	O
could	O
be	O
much	O
more	O
potent	O
than	O
annual	SET
human	O
virus	DIS
because	O
,	O
in	O
effect	O
,	O
people	O
's	O
bodies	O
had	O
``	O
forgotten	O
''	O
it	O
.	O
Professor	O
Albert	PERSON
Osterhaus	PERSON
said	O
:	O
``	O
The	DIS
virus	DIS
is	O
in	O
an	O
evolutionary	O
stasis	O
,	O
apparently	O
for	O
5	DURATION
years	DURATION
.	O
If	O
this	O
continued	O
for	O
another	O
5	NUMBER
or	O
10	DURATION
years	DURATION
and	O
then	O
it	O
came	O
back	O
into	O
human	O
population	O
,	O
then	O
immunity	O
may	O
have	O
dwindled	O
.	O
That	O
's	O
an	O
interesting	O
thing	O
to	O
realize	O
.	O
``	O
The	DIS
-LSB-	O
influenza	DIS
-RSB-	O
B	DIS
virus	DIS
is	O
not	O
a	O
mild	O
virus	DIS
.	O
For	O
example	O
,	O
in	O
Netherlands	LOCATION
more	O
people	O
die	O
of	O
flu	O
than	O
in	O
road	O
accidents	O
.	O
These	O
flu	O
deaths	O
are	O
caused	O
by	O
B	DIS
viruses	O
.	O
These	O
are	O
dangerous	O
viruses	O
.	O
''	O
However	O
,	O
Dr	PERSON
Hay	PERSON
noted	O
:	O
``	O
One	NUMBER
of	O
major	O
requirements	O
for	O
infection	O
is	O
close	O
contact	O
and	O
we	O
do	O
n't	O
go	O
around	O
kissing	O
seals	VIC
,	O
do	O
we	O
?	O
''	O
In	O
1999	DATE
,	O
the	VIC
Dutch	VIC
scientists	O
found	O
12	VIC
seal	VIC
pups	VIC
with	O
breathing	O
difficulties	O
,	O
stranded	O
on	O
coast	O
.	O
They	O
took	O
the	VIC
seal	VIC
pups	VIC
to	O
Seal	ORGANIZATION
Rehabilitation	ORGANIZATION
and	ORGANIZATION
Research	ORGANIZATION
Center	ORGANIZATION
in	O
Pieterburen	LOCATION
and	O
tested	O
them	O
for	O
viruses	O
.	O
Surprisingly	O
they	O
found	O
influenza	DIS
B	DIS
and	O
are	O
confident	O
they	O
have	O
ruled	O
out	O
possibility	O
of	O
laboratory	O
contamination	O
.	O
They	O
then	O
tested	O
971	NUMBER
stored	O
blood	O
samples	O
,	O
taken	O
from	O
seals	VIC
admitted	O
to	O
center	O
since	O
1980s	DATE
.	O
Before	O
1995	DATE
,	O
none	O
of	O
580	NUMBER
samples	O
contained	O
influenza	DIS
B	DIS
.	O
But	O
from	O
1995	DATE
onwards	O
2	PERCENT
percent	PERCENT
of	O
391	NUMBER
samples	O
showed	O
evidence	O
of	O
virus	DIS
.	O
This	O
-LSB-	O
these	O
-RSB-	O
data	O
,	O
and	O
fact	O
virus	DIS
was	O
a	O
1995	DATE
strain	O
,	O
shows	O
the	VIC
seals	VIC
caught	O
a	O
human	O
virus	DIS
in	O
1995	DATE
.	O
Professor	O
Osterhaus	PERSON
thought	O
it	O
unlikely	O
infection	O
occurred	O
in	O
a	O
rehabilitation	O
center	O
as	O
workers	O
wear	O
protective	O
clothes	O
and	O
take	O
other	O
precautions	O
:	O
``	O
I	O
think	O
its	O
much	O
more	O
likely	O
someone	O
found	O
a	O
seal	VIC
stranded	O
on	O
a	O
beach	O
and	O
accidentally	O
coughed	O
into	O
its	O
face	O
.	O
''	O
The	DIS
research	O
is	O
published	O
in	O
journal	O
Science	O
.	O
The	DIS
original	O
article	O
discussed	O
above	O
is	O
A.D.M.E.	PERSON
Osterhaus	PERSON
,	O
G.F.	PERSON
Rimmelzwaan	PERSON
,	O
B.E.E.	PERSON
Martina	PERSON
,	O
T.M.	PERSON
Bestebroer	PERSON
,	O
and	O
R.A.M.	PERSON
Fouchier	PERSON
.	O
Influenza	O
B	DIS
virus	DIS
in	O
seals	VIC
.	O
Science	O
May	DATE
12	VIC
2000	DATE
:	O
1051-1053	DURATION
.	O
-	O
Man	O
.	O
Ed	PERSON
.	O
DS	O
-RSB-	O
...	O
tg/ds	O
--	O
year	DURATION
;	O
however	O
,	O
the	O
identification	O
of	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus	VIC
in	O
a	VIC
horse	VIC
is	O
a	VIC
reminder	O
that	O
the	O
virus	VIC
is	O
here	O
we	O
all	O
need	O
to	O
take	O
precautions	O
,	O
''	O
Williams	PERSON
said	O
.	O
``	O
Since	O
the	O
majority	O
of	O
human	VIC
and	VIC
veterinary	VIC
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus	VIC
cases	VIC
occurred	O
from	O
June	DATE
through	DATE
September	DATE
-LSB-	O
in	O
2002	DATE
-RSB-	O
,	O
a	VIC
positive	VIC
horse	VIC
case	VIC
this	O
early	O
is	O
a	VIC
little	O
surprising	O
,	O
but	O
some	O
other	O
states	O
have	O
already	O
seen	O
positive	VIC
horses	VIC
,	O
birds	VIC
,	O
even	VIC
mosquitoes	VIC
.	O
It	O
's	O
certainly	O
not	O
too	O
early	O
to	O
start	O
protecting	O
yourself	O
your	O
loved	O
ones	O
from	O
mosquito	O
bites	O
.	O
We	O
especially	O
urge	O
protecting	O
our	O
senior	O
citizens	O
,	O
who	O
are	O
at	O
greater	O
risk	O
of	O
the	O
more	O
serious	O
form	O
of	O
the	O
disease	O
.	O
''	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus	VIC
is	O
a	VIC
mosquito-borne	O
infection	O
that	O
can	O
cause	O
encephalitis	DIS
-LRB-	O
inflammation	O
of	O
the	O
brain	O
-RRB-	O
or	O
meningitis	O
-LRB-	O
inflammation	O
of	O
the	O
lining	O
of	O
the	O
brain	O
spinal	O
cord	O
-RRB-	O
.	O
However	O
,	O
less	O
than	O
one	PERCENT
percent	PERCENT
of	O
persons	O
bitten	O
by	O
an	O
infected	O
mosquito	O
experience	O
severe	O
illness	O
.	O
Most	O
people	O
infected	O
with	O
diseases	O
transmitted	O
by	O
mosquitoes	VIC
--	O
including	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus	VIC
--	O
experience	O
no	O
symptoms	O
or	O
have	O
only	O
mild	O
symptoms	O
such	O
as	O
fever	O
headaches	O
.	O
More	O
severe	O
infection	O
can	O
include	O
high	O
fever	O
,	O
severe	O
headache	O
,	O
stiff	O
neck	O
,	O
altered	O
mental	O
state	O
,	O
death	O
.	O
Although	O
those	O
over	O
50	DURATION
years	DURATION
of	O
age	O
are	O
more	O
likely	O
to	O
have	O
severe	O
infections	O
,	O
anyone	O
who	O
develops	O
symptoms	O
should	O
consult	O
a	VIC
physician	O
.	O
The	O
Arkansas	ORGANIZATION
Department	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
will	O
begin	O
surveillance	O
for	O
West	VIC
Nile	VIC
virus	VIC
in	O
dead	O
blue	O
jays	O
crows	O
on	O
Mon	DATE
19	DATE
May	DATE
2003	DATE
.	O
Citizens	O
may	O
bring	O
birds	VIC
of	O
these	O
species	O
to	O
their	O
county	O
health	O
unit	O
.	O
Testing	O
will	O
end	O
in	O
a	VIC
county	O
once	DATE
a	VIC
positive	VIC
bird	O
is	O
confirmed	O
,	O
we	O
know	O
virus	VIC
is	O
present	DATE
in	O
the	O
county	O
.	O
Netherlands	O
There	O
have	O
been	O
a	O
number	O
of	O
cases	O
of	O
meningococcal	O
disease	O
which	O
are	O
associated	O
with	O
returnees	O
from	O
the	O
Haj	O
and	O
their	O
close	O
contacts	O
.	O
France	LOCATION
-	O
Update	O
.	O
The	O
number	O
of	O
cases	O
of	O
meningococcal	O
disease	O
associated	O
with	O
pilgrims	O
who	O
have	O
travelled	O
for	O
the	O
Haj	O
has	O
increased	O
,	O
and	O
the	O
total	O
number	O
of	O
cases	O
to	O
date	O
is	O
14	NUMBER
,	O
including	O
4	NUMBER
deaths	O
.	O
Eleven	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
confirmed	O
cases	O
were	O
of	O
meningococcal	O
serogroup	O
W135	O
.	O
United	LOCATION
Kingdom	LOCATION
-	O
Update	O
.	O
The	O
number	O
of	O
cases	O
of	O
meningococcal	O
disease	O
linked	O
to	O
pilgrims	O
has	O
increased	O
,	O
and	O
is	O
now	DATE
22	NUMBER
with	O
4	NUMBER
deaths	O
.	O
Twenty	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
confirmed	O
cases	O
are	O
of	O
meningococcal	O
serogroup	O
W135	O
and	O
1	NUMBER
of	O
_	NUMBER
N.	O
meningitidis	DIS
_	O
serogroup	O
A	VIC
.	O
The	O
onset	O
of	O
the	O
last	O
case	O
of	O
meningococcal	O
disease	O
reported	O
to	O
date	O
-LRB-	O
in	O
a	O
contact	O
-RRB-	O
was	O
on	O
11	DATE
April	DATE
.	O
Oman	LOCATION
.	O
There	O
have	O
been	O
12	NUMBER
cases	O
to	O
date	O
,	O
all	O
have	O
recovered	O
.	O
Of	O
these	O
,	O
3	NUMBER
were	O
pilgrims	O
-LRB-	O
2	NUMBER
males	O
aged	O
40	NUMBER
and	O
55	VIC
years	DURATION
and	O
1	NUMBER
female	VIC
aged	O
60	DURATION
years	DURATION
-RRB-	O
returning	O
from	O
the	O
Haj	O
,	O
and	O
9	NUMBER
cases	O
were	O
close	O
contacts	O
of	O
those	O
returned	O
from	O
the	O
Haj	O
.	O
The	O
ages	O
of	O
these	O
patients	O
ranged	O
from	O
6	DURATION
months	DURATION
to	O
80	DURATION
years	DURATION
.	O
The	O
date	O
of	O
onset	O
of	O
the	O
first	ORDINAL
case	O
was	O
20	DATE
March	DATE
,	O
and	O
the	O
most	O
recent	O
case	O
was	O
reported	O
on	O
6	DATE
April	DATE
.	O
Seven	NUMBER
of	O
the	O
confirmed	O
cases	O
are	O
of	O
meningococcal	O
serogroup	O
W135	O
and	O
2	NUMBER
of	O
_	NUMBER
Neisseria	DIS
meningitidis	DIS
_	O
serogroup	O
A.	LOCATION
Saudi	LOCATION
Arabia	LOCATION
.	O
A	VIC
total	O
of	O
199	NUMBER
cases	O
with	O
55	VIC
deaths	O
has	O
been	O
reported	O
since	O
the	O
Haj	DATE
last	DATE
month	DATE
.	O
Bacteriological	O
investigations	O
have	O
revealed	O
_	O
N.	O
meningitidis	DIS
_	NUMBER
serogroup	O
A	VIC
in	O
55	VIC
cases	O
,	O
serogroup	O
W135	O
in	O
30	NUMBER
and	O
serogroup	O
B	DIS
in	O
1	NUMBER
case	O
.	O
A	VIC
record	O
number	O
of	O
pilgrims	O
-LRB-	O
around	O
1.3	NUMBER
million	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
travelled	O
to	O
Saudi	LOCATION
Arabia	LOCATION
for	O
the	O
Haj	O
this	DATE
year	DATE
,	O
with	O
an	O
increase	O
in	O
the	O
number	O
from	O
South-East	LOCATION
Asia	LOCATION
.	O
Case	O
management	O
and	O
contact	O
tracing	O
are	O
taking	O
place	O
.	O
Netherlands	LOCATION
.	O
There	O
have	O
been	O
2	NUMBER
confirmed	O
cases	O
and	O
1	NUMBER
probable	O
case	O
of	O
meningococcal	O
disease	O
in	O
close	O
contacts	O
of	O
pilgrims	O
returning	O
from	O
the	O
Haj	O
.	O
The	O
dates	O
of	O
onset	O
in	O
the	O
confirmed	O
cases	O
were	O
5	NUMBER
and	O
6	DATE
April	DATE
.	O
Serogroup	DIS
W135	O
_	O
Neisseria	DIS
meningitidis	DIS
_	O
has	O
been	O
isolated	O
from	O
both	O
.	O
Meningococcal	O
disease	O
.	O
As	O
with	O
all	O
types	O
of	O
meningococcal	O
disease	O
,	O
early	O
diagnosis	O
and	O
treatment	O
are	O
essential	O
.	O
The	O
symptoms	O
of	O
group	O
W135	O
meningococcal	O
disease	O
are	O
the	O
same	O
as	O
for	O
other	O
groups	O
of	O
the	O
disease	O
:	O
sudden	O
onset	O
of	O
intense	O
headache	O
,	O
high	O
fever	O
,	O
nausea	O
,	O
and	O
vomiting	O
,	O
photophobia	O
and	O
stiff	O
neck	O
.	O
The	O
most	O
severe	O
clinical	O
form	O
of	O
the	O
disease	O
,	O
meningococcal	O
septicaemia	O
can	O
be	O
presented	O
by	O
abrupt	O
onset	O
,	O
high	O
fever	O
,	O
petechial	O
rash	O
or	O
purpura	O
.	O
WHO	O
recommends	O
that	O
chemoprophylaxis	O
be	O
given	O
to	O
close	O
contacts	O
of	O
the	O
cases	O
,	O
such	O
as	O
persons	O
sleeping	O
in	O
the	O
same	O
dwelling	O
.	O
In	O
most	O
countries	O
rifampicin	O
is	O
recommended	O
.	O
Immunization	O
against	O
meningococcal	O
disease	O
A+C	O
has	O
been	O
an	O
entry	O
requirement	O
by	O
Saudi	LOCATION
Arabia	LOCATION
for	O
pilgrims	O
travelling	O
to	O
the	O
Haj	O
.	O
However	O
,	O
the	O
meningococcal	O
A+C	O
vaccine	O
does	O
not	O
protect	O
against	O
group	O
W135	O
infection	O
.	O
WHO	O
encourages	O
national	O
reference	O
laboratories	O
to	O
closely	O
monitor	O
meningococcal	O
disease	O
.	O
Germany	LOCATION
.	O
A	VIC
55	VIC
year-old	VIC
female	VIC
of	O
Turkish	MISC
nationality	O
living	O
in	O
Germany	LOCATION
returned	O
from	O
Saudi	LOCATION
Arabia	LOCATION
on	O
28th	DATE
March	DATE
.	O
She	O
was	O
not	O
feeling	O
well	O
in	O
the	O
plane	O
and	O
was	O
admitted	O
to	O
a	O
local	O
hospital	O
after	O
landing	O
in	O
Cologne	LOCATION
in	O
reduced	O
general	O
condition	O
.	O
A	VIC
meningitis	DIS
was	O
diagnosed	O
and	O
treatment	O
started	O
.	O
According	O
to	O
her	O
husband	O
she	O
had	O
been	O
vaccinated	O
for	O
meningococci	O
.	O
Neisseria	DIS
meningitidis	DIS
Serogroup	DIS
B	DIS
,	O
Serotype	DIS
2a	DIS
and	O
Subtype	DIS
PI	O
.2	NUMBER
was	O
confirmed	O
by	O
a	O
national	O
reference	O
laboratory	O
.	O
--	O
Prof.	O
Pramod	PERSON
M.	PERSON
Shah	PERSON
Frankfurt	LOCATION
Germany	LOCATION
e-mail	O
:	O
shah@em.uni-frankfurt.de......................................jw	O
/	O
es	O
--	O
Confirmed	O
in	O
the	O
United	LOCATION
States	LOCATION
All	O
information	O
in	O
the	O
following	O
Notice	O
marked	O
with	O
an	O
asterisk	O
-LRB-	O
*	O
-RRB-	O
identifies	O
changes	O
since	O
the	O
last	O
Notice	O
was	O
sent	O
out	O
.	O
Exotic	DIS
Newcastle	DIS
disease	DIS
-LRB-	O
END	DIS
-RRB-	O
was	O
confirmed	O
on	O
1	DATE
Oct	DATE
2002	DATE
in	O
the	O
State	O
of	O
California	LOCATION
,	O
and	O
has	O
now	DATE
spread	O
beyond	O
backyard	O
flocks	O
to	O
affect	O
22	NUMBER
commercial	O
operations	O
in	O
California	LOCATION
.	O
On	O
16	DATE
Jan	DATE
2003	DATE
,	O
END	DIS
was	O
also	O
confirmed	O
in	O
a	O
backyard	O
flock	O
in	O
the	O
State	O
of	O
Nevada	LOCATION
.	O
A	O
backyard	O
flock	O
was	O
confirmed	O
with	O
END	DIS
on	O
4	DATE
Feb	DATE
2003	DATE
,	O
in	O
the	O
State	O
of	O
Arizona	LOCATION
.	O
Clinical	O
signs	O
in	O
infected	VIC
birds	VIC
include	O
respiratory	O
,	O
nervous	O
,	O
and	O
gastrointestinal	O
signs	O
.	O
Mortality	O
is	O
up	O
to	O
90	PERCENT
percent	PERCENT
of	O
exposed	O
birds	VIC
.	O
Investigations	O
are	O
ongoing	O
and	O
all	O
figures	O
are	O
pending	O
final	O
validation	O
.	O
Animal	O
and	O
Plant	ORGANIZATION
Health	ORGANIZATION
Inspection	ORGANIZATION
Service	ORGANIZATION
-LRB-	O
APHIS	ORGANIZATION
-RRB-	O
personnel	O
and	O
other	O
federal	O
government	O
personnel	O
are	O
working	O
with	O
the	O
States	LOCATION
to	O
consider	O
additional	O
resources	O
to	O
meet	O
the	O
labor	O
demands	O
at	O
the	O
Task	O
Forces	O
.	O
APHIS	ORGANIZATION
has	O
developed	O
a	O
plan	O
for	O
national	O
END	DIS
surveillance	O
.	O
This	O
plan	O
will	O
enhance	O
the	O
already	O
extensive	O
surveillance	O
underway	O
.	O
*	O
Situation	O
Update	O
-LRB-	O
as	O
of	O
8:00	TIME
p.m.	TIME
PST	TIME
,	TIME
1	TIME
Apr	DATE
2003	DATE
-RRB-	O
Arizona	LOCATION
/	O
California	LOCATION
/	O
Nevada	LOCATION
/	O
Grand	O
Total	O
Number	O
of	O
premises	O
quarantined	O
:	O
6	NUMBER
/	O
15	NUMBER
395	NUMBER
/	O
154	NUMBER
/	O
15	NUMBER
555	NUMBER
Number	O
of	O
premises	O
positive	O
:	O
*	O
1	NUMBER
/	O
878	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
no	O
change	O
since	O
3/31	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
/	O
**	O
10	NUMBER
/	O
889	NUMBER
-LRB-	O
no	O
change	O
since	O
3/31	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Number	O
of	O
contact	O
premises	O
:	O
3	NUMBER
/	O
1542	DATE
-LRB-	O
down	O
4	NUMBER
from	O
4/1	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
/	O
128	NUMBER
/	O
1673	DATE
-LRB-	O
down	O
4	NUMBER
from	O
4/1	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
Number	O
of	O
premises	O
depopulated	O
:	O
4	NUMBER
/	O
2331	DATE
/	O
138	NUMBER
/	O
2473	DATE
Premises	O
waiting	O
to	O
be	O
depopulated	O
:	O
0	NUMBER
/	DATE
89	DATE
/	DATE
0	DATE
/	DATE
89	DATE
Birds	O
depopulated	O
to	O
date	O
:	O
269	NUMBER
/	O
3	NUMBER
329	NUMBER
055	NUMBER
/	O
2746	DATE
/	O
3	NUMBER
332	NUMBER
070	NUMBER
Counties	O
-LSB-	O
in	O
California	LOCATION
-RSB-	O
with	O
quarantined	O
premises	O
:	O
La	PERSON
Paz	PERSON
,	O
Los	LOCATION
Angeles	LOCATION
,	O
Riverside	LOCATION
,	O
Orange	LOCATION
,	O
San	LOCATION
Bernardino	LOCATION
,	O
San	LOCATION
Diego	LOCATION
,	O
Clark	PERSON
*	O
The	O
last	O
infected	VIC
premises	O
in	O
Arizona	LOCATION
was	O
depopulated	O
on	O
7	DATE
Feb	DATE
2003	DATE
.	O
**	O
The	O
last	O
infected	VIC
premises	O
in	O
Nevada	LOCATION
was	O
depopulated	O
on	O
29	DATE
Jan	DATE
2003	DATE
.	O
Effective	O
17	DATE
Jan	DATE
2003	DATE
,	O
APHIS	ORGANIZATION
imposed	O
a	O
federal	O
quarantine	O
that	O
regulates	O
the	O
interstate	O
movement	O
of	O
all	O
species	O
of	O
birds	VIC
and	O
poultry	O
products	O
from	O
Clark	PERSON
and	O
a	O
portion	O
of	O
Nye	LOCATION
County	LOCATION
,	O
NV	O
.	O
Effective	O
10	DATE
Feb	DATE
2003	DATE
,	O
APHIS	ORGANIZATION
imposed	O
a	O
federal	O
quarantine	O
that	O
regulates	O
the	O
interstate	O
movement	O
of	O
all	O
species	O
of	O
birds	VIC
and	O
poultry	O
products	O
from	O
all	O
of	O
La	LOCATION
Paz	LOCATION
and	O
Yuma	LOCATION
Counties	O
and	O
a	O
portion	O
of	O
Mohave	LOCATION
County	LOCATION
,	O
AZ.	LOCATION
.	O
The	O
U.S.	ORGANIZATION
Department	ORGANIZATION
of	ORGANIZATION
Agriculture	ORGANIZATION
-LRB-	O
USDA	ORGANIZATION
-RRB-	O
has	O
declared	O
an	O
extraordinary	O
emergency	O
for	O
the	O
States	O
of	O
Arizona	LOCATION
,	O
California	LOCATION
,	O
and	O
Nevada	LOCATION
.	O
These	O
declarations	O
allow	O
USDA	ORGANIZATION
to	O
apply	O
federal	O
authority	O
within	O
Arizona	LOCATION
,	O
California	LOCATION
and	O
Nevada	LOCATION
.	O
Currently	DATE
there	O
are	O
22	NUMBER
commercial	O
flocks	O
in	O
the	O
State	O
of	O
California	LOCATION
affected	O
by	O
END	DIS
.	O
The	O
breakdown	O
of	O
the	O
commercial	O
premises	O
involved	O
is	O
as	O
follows	O
:	O
4	NUMBER
premises	O
in	O
Riverside	LOCATION
County	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
3	NUMBER
infected	VIC
and	O
1	NUMBER
contact	O
-RRB-	O
,	O
7	NUMBER
premises	O
in	O
San	LOCATION
Diego	LOCATION
County	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
7	NUMBER
infected	VIC
-RRB-	O
,	O
and	O
11	NUMBER
premises	O
in	O
San	LOCATION
Bernardino	LOCATION
County	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
11	NUMBER
infected	VIC
-RRB-	O
.	O
*	O
Of	O
the	O
2562	DATE
premises	O
designated	O
for	O
depopulation	O
,	O
96.5	PERCENT
percent	PERCENT
have	O
been	O
completed	O
.	O
The	O
Inland	LOCATION
Desert	LOCATION
and	O
South	O
Coast	O
ICPs	O
have	O
realigned	O
their	O
service	O
territories	O
so	O
that	O
all	O
of	O
Los	LOCATION
Angeles	LOCATION
County	LOCATION
will	O
now	DATE
be	O
handled	O
by	O
the	O
South	ORGANIZATION
Coast	ORGANIZATION
ICP	ORGANIZATION
.	O
The	O
South	ORGANIZATION
Coast	ORGANIZATION
ICP	ORGANIZATION
also	O
will	O
be	O
responsible	O
for	O
all	O
of	O
San	LOCATION
Diego	LOCATION
County	LOCATION
,	O
except	O
in	O
cases	O
involving	O
commercial	O
premises	O
.	O
Previously	DATE
,	O
the	O
Inland	LOCATION
Desert	LOCATION
ICP	LOCATION
handled	O
portion	O
of	O
Los	LOCATION
Angeles	LOCATION
County	LOCATION
,	O
as	O
well	O
as	O
certain	O
areas	O
of	O
San	LOCATION
Diego	LOCATION
County	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
both	O
backyard	O
and	O
commercial	O
premises	O
-RRB-	O
.	O
The	O
Central	ORGANIZATION
Valley	ORGANIZATION
Incident	ORGANIZATION
Command	ORGANIZATION
Post	ORGANIZATION
in	O
Modesto	LOCATION
,	O
CA	LOCATION
,	O
is	O
staffed	O
and	O
working	O
cooperatively	O
with	O
approximately	O
15	NUMBER
-RRB-	O
20	NUMBER
county	O
officials	O
to	O
implement	O
efficient	O
surveillance	O
measures	O
throughout	O
the	O
Central	LOCATION
Valley	LOCATION
.	O
Outreach	O
Activities	O
:	O
On	O
a	O
daily	SET
basis	O
,	O
Task	O
Force	O
personnel	O
are	O
communicating	O
information	O
concerning	O
surveillance	O
,	O
depopulation	O
,	O
and	O
cleaning	O
and	O
disinfection	O
operations	O
to	O
all	O
affected	O
city	O
managers	O
in	O
Southern	LOCATION
California	LOCATION
.	O
Currently	DATE
,	O
Task	O
Force	O
information	O
personnel	O
field	O
approximately	O
450	NUMBER
calls	O
per	O
week	DURATION
from	O
the	O
public	O
through	O
the	O
Joint	ORGANIZATION
Information	ORGANIZATION
Center	ORGANIZATION
phone	O
bank	O
.	O
This	O
is	O
a	O
20-fold	O
increase	O
from	O
the	O
number	O
of	O
calls	O
in	O
October	DATE
2002	DATE
.	O
On	O
average	O
,	O
approximately	O
300	NUMBER
of	O
these	O
calls	O
require	O
follow-up	O
action	O
by	O
the	O
Inland	LOCATION
Desert	LOCATION
or	O
South	O
Coast	O
Incident	O
Command	O
Posts	O
.	O
The	O
Task	O
Force	O
information	O
staff	O
provides	O
daily	SET
updates	O
to	O
approximately	O
50	NUMBER
media	O
outlets	O
in	O
California	LOCATION
.	O
In	O
addition	O
,	O
in	O
Area	O
Command	O
alone	O
,	O
the	O
information	O
staff	O
field	O
approximately	O
70	NUMBER
media	O
calls	O
per	O
week	DURATION
.	O
Caltrans	ORGANIZATION
is	O
in	O
the	O
process	O
of	O
placing	O
posters	O
with	O
information	O
on	O
END	DIS
and	O
related	O
quarantine	O
restrictions	O
at	O
approximately	O
100	NUMBER
highway	O
rest	O
areas	O
throughout	O
California	LOCATION
.	O
The	O
following	O
link	O
is	O
to	O
the	O
State	O
of	O
California	LOCATION
's	O
END	DIS
website	O
.	O
<	O
http://www.cdfa.ca.gov/ahfss/ah/Newcastle_info.htm	O
>	O
The	O
following	O
link	O
is	O
to	O
the	O
State	O
of	O
Nevada	LOCATION
's	O
END	DIS
website	O
.	O
<	O
http://www.agri.state.nv.us/END.htm	O
>	O
The	O
following	O
link	O
is	O
to	O
the	O
State	O
of	O
Arizona	LOCATION
's	O
END	DIS
website	O
.	O
<	O
http://agriculture.state.az.us/newcastle.htm	NUMBER
>	O
Please	O
forward	O
this	O
information	O
to	O
your	O
federal	O
,	O
State	ORGANIZATION
,	O
and	O
industry	O
counterparts	O
as	O
necessary	O
.	O
If	O
you	O
have	O
any	O
questions	O
about	O
this	O
situation	O
,	O
please	O
feel	O
free	O
to	O
call	O
USDA	ORGANIZATION
,	O
APHIS	LOCATION
,	O
VS	O
,	O
Emergency	ORGANIZATION
Programs	ORGANIZATION
at	O
800-940-6524	NUMBER
,	O
301-734-8073	NUMBER
,	O
or	O
e-mail	O
atEMOC@APHIS.USDA.GOV	O
.	O
definitions	O
-------	NUMBER
Emergency	O
Management	O
Issue	O
is	O
for	O
information	O
with	O
no	O
impact	O
on	O
APHIS	ORGANIZATION
Emergency	ORGANIZATION
Management	ORGANIZATION
Notice	ORGANIZATION
is	O
an	O
ongoing	O
incident	O
with	O
potential	O
impact	O
on	O
APHIS	ORGANIZATION
Emergency	ORGANIZATION
Management	ORGANIZATION
Warning	ORGANIZATION
is	O
an	O
ongoing	O
incident	O
with	O
almost	O
certain	O
impact	O
on	O
APHIS	ORGANIZATION
A	O
ProMED-mail	O
<	O
http://www.promedmail.org	NUMBER
>	O
ProMED-mail	O
,	O
a	O
program	O
of	O
International	ORGANIZATION
Society	ORGANIZATION
for	O
Infectious	O
Diseases	O
<	O
http://www.isid.org	NUMBER
>	O
Is	O
it	O
possible	O
to	O
say	O
whether	O
the	DIS
H7	DIS
strain	DIS
isolated	O
in	O
Delaware	LOCATION
outbreak	O
has	O
been	O
classified	O
as	O
highly	O
pathogenic	O
avian	DIS
influenza	DIS
,	O
as	O
literature	O
states	O
that	O
H7	DIS
and	O
H5	O
subtypes	O
can	O
be	O
of	O
high	O
or	O
low	O
pathogenicity	O
?	O
-LSB-	O
Currently	DATE
the	DIS
avian	DIS
influenza	DIS
in	O
Delaware	LOCATION
is	O
considered	O
low	O
pathogenicity	O
,	O
but	O
virus	O
is	O
being	O
carefully	O
monitored	O
.	O
Low	O
pathogenic	O
strains	O
can	O
mutate	O
to	O
highly	O
pathogenic	O
strains	O
.	O
Consequently	O
,	O
it	O
is	O
beneficial	O
to	O
eliminate	O
infected	O
flocks	O
,	O
and	O
to	O
closely	O
monitor	O
virus	O
.	O
-	O
Mod.TG	O
-RSB-	O
-------------------------------------------	NUMBER
.	O
Preliminary	O
test	O
results	O
indicate	O
the	O
deaths	O
of	O
more	VIC
than	VIC
65	VIC
dolphins	VIC
in	O
the	O
Panhandle	LOCATION
may	O
have	O
been	O
caused	O
by	O
biotoxin	DIS
released	O
by	O
naturally	DIS
occurring	DIS
algae	DIS
.	O
Domoic	O
acid	DIS
has	O
been	O
blamed	O
for	O
several	O
marine	O
mammal	O
deaths	O
on	O
the	O
West	LOCATION
Coast	LOCATION
,	O
she	O
said	O
.	O
-LSB-	O
An	O
excellent	O
review	O
of	O
domoic	DIS
acid	DIS
in	O
mammals	O
can	O
be	O
found	O
in	O
``	O
Mammal	O
,	O
bird	O
die-off	O
,	O
domoic	DIS
acid	DIS
-	O
USA	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
CA	O
-RRB-	O
-LRB-02-RRB-20020708	O
.4702	NUMBER
.	O
''	O
Domoic	O
acid	DIS
is	O
a	DIS
neurotoxic	DIS
tricarboxylic	DIS
amino	DIS
acid	DIS
structurally	O
related	O
to	O
kainic	O
and	O
glutamic	O
acids	O
.	O
It	O
was	O
chemically	O
identified	O
after	O
its	O
isolation	O
in	O
1958	DATE
from	O
the	O
seaweed	O
_	O
Chondria	O
armata	O
_	O
,	O
found	O
off	O
the	O
coast	O
of	O
Japan	LOCATION
.	O
In	O
1987	DATE
,	O
more	VIC
than	VIC
100	NUMBER
people	O
became	O
ill	O
and	O
several	O
people	O
died	O
following	O
the	O
consumption	O
of	O
blue	O
mussels	O
caught	O
off	O
Prince	LOCATION
Edward	LOCATION
Island	LOCATION
,	O
Canada	LOCATION
.	O
Canadian	MISC
scientists	O
found	O
that	O
domoic	DIS
acid	DIS
had	O
entered	O
the	O
food	O
chain	O
when	O
the	O
mussels	O
fed	O
on	O
a	DIS
toxic	O
algal	O
bloom	O
of	O
the	O
pennate	O
diatom	O
_	NUMBER
Pseudonitzschia	O
pungens	O
_	O
forma	O
multiseries	O
.	O
-	O
Mod.TG	O
-RSB-	O
Australia	LOCATION
-LRB-	O
NSW	O
-RRB-	O
20030509.1157	NUMBER
,	O
''	O
had	O
one	NUMBER
significant	O
misleading	O
fact	O
and	O
a	O
few	O
questionable	O
elements	O
.	O
I	O
realize	O
the	O
source	O
was	O
a	O
local	O
newspaper	O
,	O
and	O
therefore	O
it	O
is	O
important	O
to	O
address	O
some	O
of	O
the	O
less	O
accurate	O
elements	O
of	O
this	O
report	O
.	O
It	O
was	O
stated	O
that	O
the	O
disease	O
is	O
not	O
transferred	O
from	O
person	O
to	O
person	O
.	O
While	O
person-to-person	O
transmission	O
of	O
the	O
organisms	O
is	O
not	O
common	O
,	O
it	O
has	O
been	O
reported	O
over	O
the	DURATION
years	DURATION
.	O
Person-to-person	O
spread	O
of	O
the	O
disease	O
does	O
occur	O
,	O
as	O
is	O
evident	O
from	O
the	O
1943	DATE
Louisiana	LOCATION
outbreak	O
,	O
when	O
a	O
single	O
fatal	O
human	O
case	O
gave	O
rise	O
to	O
18	NUMBER
additional	O
human	O
cases	O
among	O
nursing	O
attendants	O
at	O
the	O
hospital	O
.	O
Interhuman	MISC
transmission	O
of	O
psittacosis	O
was	O
also	O
reported	O
by	O
Hansen	PERSON
et	O
al.	O
in	O
the	O
Danish	MISC
Med	MISC
Bul	MISC
.	O
1955	DATE
Vol	O
2	NUMBER
page	O
51	NUMBER
.	O
It	O
is	O
correct	O
that	O
*	O
experimental	O
*	O
hosts	O
of	O
this	O
disease	O
can	O
include	O
all	O
species	O
of	O
birds	VIC
;	O
however	O
,	O
it	O
is	O
important	O
to	O
distinguish	O
between	O
experimental	O
disease	O
transmission	O
and	O
natural	O
occurrence	O
of	O
the	O
disease	O
.	O
I	O
would	O
therefore	O
question	O
the	O
claim	O
that	O
``	O
all	O
birds	VIC
are	O
susceptible	O
to	O
the	O
infection	O
.	O
''	O
The	O
response	O
of	O
different	O
species	O
of	O
birds	VIC
is	O
not	O
uniform	O
,	O
and	O
some	O
are	O
highly	O
resistant	O
to	O
the	O
disease	O
.	O
In	O
some	O
species	O
of	O
birds	VIC
the	O
disease	O
has	O
never	O
been	O
reported	O
.	O
Highly	O
resistant	O
species	O
of	O
birds	VIC
do	O
not	O
impose	O
the	O
same	O
human	O
health	O
risk	O
,	O
because	O
they	O
either	O
do	O
not	O
shed	O
the	O
organism	O
or	O
harbour	O
only	O
a	O
small	O
number	O
of	O
these	O
bacteria	O
.	O
While	O
the	O
time	O
from	O
exposure	O
to	O
development	O
of	O
symptoms	O
is	O
usually	O
4-14	NUMBER
days	DURATION
as	O
stated	O
in	O
the	O
article	O
,	O
longer	O
incubation	O
periods	O
-LRB-	O
up	DURATION
to	DURATION
4	DURATION
weeks	DURATION
-RRB-	O
have	O
been	O
reported	O
in	O
humans	O
in	O
the	O
literature	O
.	O
It	O
is	O
